<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faith of the Catholick church, concerning the Eucharist Invincibly proved by the argument used against the Protestants, in the books of the faith of the perpetuity, written by Mr. Arnaud. A translation from the French.</title>
            <author>Bruzeau, Paul.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5241A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897622</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137243</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137243)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2509:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faith of the Catholick church, concerning the Eucharist Invincibly proved by the argument used against the Protestants, in the books of the faith of the perpetuity, written by Mr. Arnaud. A translation from the French.</title>
                  <author>Bruzeau, Paul.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 271, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Holy-Rood-House,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Paul Bruzeau, cf. Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Formerly Wing F260.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Glasgow University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FAITH OF THE <hi>CATHOLICK CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> Concerning the EUCHARIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Invincibly proved by the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uſed againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, in the Books of the Faith of the Perpetuity, written by Mr.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naud.</p>
            <p>A Tranſlation from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at</hi> Holy-Rood Houſe, 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:3"/>
            <head>Errours to be Corrected,</head>
            <p>Page 40. line 18. I <hi>know not.</hi> p. 50. l. laſt r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>more eaſily.</hi> p. 89. l. 1. r. <hi>came.</hi> p. 214. l. 6. r. <hi>put out</hi> a p. 225. l. 23. r. <hi>for thoſe.</hi> P. 262. l. 3. after day. r.? l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after procedurer,? alſo l. 9. after not r. ? alſo l. 18. in ſtea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>that it was not,</hi> r. <hi>was it not.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT TO THE PROTESTANTS.</head>
            <q>
               <p>THe ſole Title of this little Book, is capable to make you ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently underſtand, that the attentive reading of it, may be of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to you. It treats of a Myſtery, on the account of which, you have been made conceive the greateſt averſion from the Catholick Church: And which you have been made to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the greateſt obſtacle of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement to it. There is no Perſon of good ſence among you who will not avow, That if your Religion be falſe in this point, you ought to forſake it; and that you ought to give no credit to your Miniſters, if it be found that in
<pb facs="tcp:137243:4"/>the matter of the Sacrament, they have made you miſtake Errour for Truth. You have no aſſurance that you are not thus miſled; for they dare not ſay that their Church is Infallible. Do not then neglect ſo eaſie means to examine whether it be ſo or not; and refuſe not a few hours application to the moſt important Affair you can have in the World, which is that of your Salvation.</p>
               <p>Your Miniſters ought not to hinder you from this application: For if you find nothing ſolid in what is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to you, you will be inclined to adhere more cloſely to them. And if on the conttary, the Truth appear to you with ſuch evidence as obliges you to embrace it: What other thing ſhould hinder it from having the ſame effect on them, but a ſelfiſh ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which ſhould not be a motive to you to follow them, but rather to forſake them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:137243:4"/>
               <p> Perhaps they will tell you, there is nothing here propoſed to you of new, nothing but the ſame Argument which Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> has anſwered; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that it's not worth your ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of it.</p>
               <p>But the contrary is true: For if here were offered to you a new Proof of any Article of our Faith, which you had not heard diſcourſed of before; you would not miſs to ſay, That you ought to expect what your Miniſters could anſwer to it: But this you cannot ſay here; for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there a Debate ſo agitate on either part as this whereof you have here the reſult.</p>
               <p>That little Book of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> where it was ſuppoſed that the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Societies believes what we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve concerning the <hi>Eucharist;</hi> while it was yet a Manuſcript, was impugned by a Manuſcript-Anſwer of Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> wherein he maintained that the ſaid Suppoſition was falſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:137243:5"/>
                  <hi>that excepting the Roman Church,</hi> Tranſubſtantiation <hi>and the Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in the</hi> Euchariſt, <hi>were two things unknown to the whole World; and that neither the</hi> Greeks, <hi>nor the</hi> Armenians, <hi>nor the</hi> Ruſſians, <hi>nor the</hi> Jacobites, <hi>nor the</hi> Ethiopians, <hi>nor generally any Chriſtian, ſave only thoſe who are ſubject to the Pope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves any thing of theſe two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, the little <hi>Perpetuity</hi> was printed, with a Refutation of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer made by Mr. <hi>Claud:</hi> In which Refutation were brought moſt clear Teſtimonies of what he had ſo boldly denied, concerning the Faith of the Chriſtians of the Eaſt. But as it was judged the contrary could not be maintained; ſo that point was not inſiſted on at length.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> ſets out a great Volume againſt that little Book: And not yielding to the Proofs that were brought againſt his Aſſertion, he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
<pb facs="tcp:137243:5"/>all what he had of Wit and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xterity to ſupport what he had aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>viz. That</hi> Tranſubſtantion <hi>and the Adoration of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in the</hi> Euchariſt, <hi>were believed in no place of the World, except in the Roman Church</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Book of Mr. <hi>Claud</hi>'s, was oppoſed the firſt of the three great Volumes of the <hi>Perpetuity;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the truth of the matter of fact im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned by him, was confirmed with ſuch force, with Proofs ſo convincing, with Teſtimonies ſo irrefragable and ſo numerous, that no Man in the World would believe that one could yet pertinaciouſly maintain a thing ſo manifeſtly falſe.</p>
               <p>But we were miſtaken in this, Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> did not yet give over, but em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed all kinds of artifices and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties to put out the eyes of thoſe of his Party, that they might not ſee the Faith of the Roman Church concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> in the moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb facs="tcp:137243:6"/>and expreſs Teſtimonies of all the Oriental Societies.</p>
               <p>But this Opiniatorneſs ſerved only to make the truth ſhine forth more brightly; for it was the cauſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing a great many more new Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and whole Books publiſhed by the <hi>Greeks</hi> in certain circumſtances, that 'tis impoſſible but the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable muſt ſuccumb if ſo be they be oblig'd to reflect ſeriouſly on them.</p>
               <p>This was made appear in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Anſwer to that Book of Mr. <hi>Clauds,</hi> and in the laſt Book of the Third Volume of the <hi>Perpetuity:</hi> And Father <hi>Paris,</hi> Canon-Regular of the Congregation of St. <hi>Genevieve,</hi> a moſt learned Divine, has made two Books on the ſame ſubject; which joyned with thoſe I have mentioned, have made this matter of fact evident in the higheſt degree.</p>
               <p>This is the fruit of that long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, which has verified that Saying of St. <hi>Auguſtin (De Civit. Dei, lib.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:137243:6"/>16. <hi>cap.</hi> 12) <hi>That God permits ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral points of the Catholick Doctrine to be impugned by Hereticks with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny artifices, to the end that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks being obliged to defend them, they may be examined more exactly, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated more clearly, and maintained more vigorouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> has written nothing ſince that time on this matter; (his laſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is in the year 1670.) And there are five Volumes which he has left unanſwered: (The laſt of theſe five Volumes is in the year 1675.) The two laſt Volumes of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> the general Anſwer, which is in 1671, and the two Books of Father <hi>Paris.</hi> And yet, Gentlemen, it is very ſtrange, that notwithſtanding of this ſilence of Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> ſo publickly notorious; it is given out amongſt you, that he has written laſt, and that his Books are not anſwered: For I know this has been ſaid by ſeveral perſons, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb facs="tcp:137243:7"/>by <hi>Madamoiſelle de Suze,</hi> to a Prieſt a Friend of min.</p>
               <p>I have ſet down to you the progreſs of this famous Debate, to let you ſee you have no reaſon to ſay in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we are expecting till our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall have taught us what is to be anſwered to this Argument. They have done all you could expect from them on this ſubject; they are exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted: They have ſpoken, they have anſwered, they have replied, they have (if I can uſe the word) duplied. So that it is no more a proceſs to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed; it's all inſtructed already, and they can do no more for their part to put it in a condition to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned on.</p>
               <p>But who ſhall be the Judge of it? It ſhall be every one of you, according to the Principles of your own Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For according to the Principles of ours, there would be no queſtion at all; becauſe on one hand our Church has all the marks, by which it has
<pb facs="tcp:137243:7"/>been judged ſince St. <hi>Augustin</hi>'s time, that we ought to acknowledge it the true Church of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> And on the other, we believe that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> has given to his Church an infallible Authority, to which every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon is bound to ſubmit. But your Church is grounded on another Maxim directly contrary; and you are made to believe, that every one of you have right to examine and judge, after all your Miniſters aſſembled in a General Synod could ſay unto you.</p>
               <p>Make uſe then of the liberty which is given you, even to the end you may be ſure if they had reaſon or not to give it you. Read and Judge; but read with ſuch attention and care, as you would bring to comprehend an Affair upon which depended the Life of one of your beſt Friends; and judge with that Conſcience and ſincerity of Heart, with which you would deſire
<pb facs="tcp:137243:8"/>to be judged, if your Life or Death depended on the Judgment they were to make of you. And indeed, there is no leſs at the ſtake in this occaſion; only with this difference, that theſe Men who ſhould Judge you, could not preſerve your Life, but for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, nor condemn you but to a Death, which ſooner or later you could not eſchew: Whereas it is of far greater importance to you to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in this proceſs, after the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that is given you of the ſame; for in judging it aright, and having nothing but God before your eyes, you may eſchew a Death which never ends; a Death which all thoſe will incur who have been made to look upon as a Damnable Errour, the Ancient and perpetual Faith of the moſt ſublime Myſtery of our Religion, and may put your ſelves in a condition to enjoy one day a Life eternally happy, after having
<pb facs="tcp:137243:8"/>received the pledge thereof by the real and true partaking of the Worlds Saviour, wherewith the Catholick Church nouriſhes her Children.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137243:9"/>
            <head>THE FAITH OF THE <hi>CATHOLICK CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> Concerning the EUCHARIST.</head>
            <head type="sub">Invincibly proved by the Argument uſed againſt the Proteſtants, in the Books of Mr <hi>Arnaud,</hi> entituled, <hi>The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of the Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THere is no Chriſtian can deny, that a Doctrine regarding one of the principal Myſteries of Religion, ſuch as is the <hi>Eucharist</hi>
               <note place="margin">* The Controverſie of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is one of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant of thoſe which makes the ſeparation betwixt the <hi>Roman Church</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants, ſays Mr.</hi> Claud, p. 1. <hi>of the Preface of his Anſwer to Mr.</hi> Arnaud. The Article of the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> in my Judgment, is one of the moſt eſſential, <hi>ſays M.</hi> de Larroque, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Rouen, <hi>in his Preface to the Hiſtory of the</hi> Euchariſt.</note>, which had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137243:10"/>been always believed in the Univerſal <hi>Church,</hi> is a Doctrine taught by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the firſt Believers We ſhall then have proved the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> ſuch as the Roman Church now believes it, to be the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, when we ſhall have proved it to be that which has always been believed in all the Churches of the World. Now it's impoſſible but it muſt have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways believed in all Churches. If being certain it was univerſally believed in ſome Ages, we can demonſtrate that it could not proceed from an innovation or change of its ancient Faith, that the Church of theſe Ages began to believe it. The buſineſs will be compleatly done then, if we can make out this: And thus we make it out.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:137243:10"/>
               <head>SECT. 1. ARGUMENT.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>All the Churches both of the Eaſt and Weſt, were found to be united in the Belief of the</hi> Real Preſence <hi>towards the beginning of the eleventh Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and they are found to be yet united in the ſame Belief, excepting onely ſome new Sects of the laſt Age.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But it is impoſſible this Belief ſhould have been eſtabliſhed of new (or by an innovation of their ancient Faith) in all theſe Churches; and yet no trace nor memorial of that Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appeared: And it is certain there has appeared none at all, neither from</hi> Paſchaſius <hi>his time, to that of</hi> Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius; <hi>nor from</hi> Berengarius <hi>his time, even to this day.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore it is certain that the Doctrine of the</hi> Real Preſence, <hi>is the perpetual Doctrine of the Church; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently none can maintain the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, without being an Heretick.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:137243:11"/>
               <p> THe firſt Propoſition, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the major, has two parts; one that the Churches of the Eaſt were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame Faith, concerning the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> with the Roman Church, in <hi>Berengarius</hi> his time: The other, that they are united with the ſame at this time.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Propoſition, which is called the minor, has likewiſe two parts: One, that ſuppoſing the truth of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, as to <hi>Berengarius</hi>'s time, it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that the innovation pretended by the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> to have been made in all Churches, from <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius,</hi> could be made in that time. The other, that if it was not made in that time in all the Eaſtern Churches, it would be impoſſible it could have been made from <hi>Berengarius</hi>'s time, to this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:137243:11"/>
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The general Proof of the major, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of</hi> Berengarius <hi>his time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>A Matter of fact unanimouſly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by contemporary Authors, who cannot be ſuſpected to have been deceived, or intending to deceive; and which has not been contradicted by thoſe who were moſt concerned to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict it, ought to be held for moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and undoubted.</p>
               <p>But we have ſhewn from the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the firſt Treatiſe of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity,</hi> and in the firſt Tome, 2 Book 7 Chap. and 9 Book 1 Chap. That all thoſe who wrote againſt <hi>Berengarius, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delmanus</hi> who had ſtudied under S. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Hugo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Langres, Deodur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Leige, Lanfrancus</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Durandus</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>Troarn Guitmondus</hi> Archbiſhop
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137243:12"/>of <hi>Averſa</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> did all of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to him, <hi>That he had ſeparated himſelf from the unity of the Holy Church; that he ſcandalized the whole Church; that none before him had drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his Follies; that his Hereſie was ſo notorious, that there needed not a Council aſſembled to condemn it; that he impugned what the Church taught througbout the World: That the</hi> Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians <hi>had not for themſelves one ſole Town, nor ſo much as one Village: And in a word, that there needed no more but to ask the</hi> Latins, <hi>the</hi> Greeks, <hi>the</hi> Armenians, <hi>and generally all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of whatſover Nation, and all would anſwer, That they believed the change of the terrestical ſubſtance of the Bread and Wine, by the infallible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and miraculous operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Omnipotence of God, into the eſſence or ſubſtance of the Lords Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We did likewiſe ſhew it was not cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, that all theſe Authors were miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137243:12"/>or knew not if there were any Churches holding <hi>Berengarius</hi> his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion or not: <hi>Lanfrancus</hi> a Native of <hi>Italy,</hi> who had been a Monk at <hi>Bec,</hi> afterwards Abbot of <hi>Caen,</hi> and at laſt Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> could bear witneſs of the Sentiments of a great part of <hi>Europe: Deoduinus</hi> and <hi>Adelmanus</hi> could ſerve as witneſſes for <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and <hi>Guitmondus</hi> for <hi>Italy,</hi> where the <hi>Greeks</hi> were mixt with the <hi>Latins;</hi> and <hi>Hugo</hi> for <hi>France.</hi> Nor can it be ſaid they intended to deceive the World, becauſe there is not any probability that ſo conſiderable Men, would have been ſo imprudent as to advance againſt their Conſcience, ſo important a matter of fact: concerning which, it had been eaſie to have covered them with ſhame, had it not been true.</p>
               <p>Finally, it is there made out farther, that neither <hi>Berengarius</hi> nor his Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, did object to theſe Authors, that their Reproaches of the novelty of their Opinion was falſe; or that it was not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137243:13"/>contrary to all the Churches of the World: That we find not they cited any Author either of the Eleventh or Tenth Age, as favourable to their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion; but were forced to go ſeek it in ſome paſſages of St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to their fancy, and in the Book of <hi>John Scot Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgene:</hi> And that they found themſelves ſo ſtraitned by that Argument of the uniform Belief of all Churches, as they had nothing to ſay, but that after the Goſpel was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to all Nations, and the World had believed it, and the Church was form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, augmented, and fructified; it fell af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards into Errour, by the ignorance of thoſe who underſtood not the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and that it was periſhed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained extant onely in their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>It ought then to be held for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and undoubted, that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches were found united in the Belief of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> in the time of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137243:13"/>of the Eleventh Age. And this is what <hi>Aubertin,</hi> lib. 9. p 943. (a moſt Learned Proteſtant) acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at leaſt as to the <hi>Latins:</hi> For he pretends that the Innovation was made in the darkneſs of the Tenth Age: That thoſe of the Eleventh had ſuckt in with their Milk, the Belief of the <hi>Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Hac Opinione una cum Lecte imbuli.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:137243:14"/>
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The particular Proof of the ſame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, in regard of the</hi> Greeks <hi>in the time of</hi> Berengarius.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMong many Proofs which may be ſeen in the Firſt Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> lib. 2. c. 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall content my ſelf with one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>During the Eleventh Century, when the Hereſie
<note place="margin">* The Hereſie of <hi>Berengarius</hi> conſiſted in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> of the Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament.</note> of <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> made ſo much noiſe in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, when it was condemned by nine Councils; whereof ſome were held in <hi>France,</hi> and ſome in <hi>Italy;</hi> the <hi>Greeks</hi> had ſeveral Churches and Monaſteries in <hi>Italy;</hi> and the <hi>Latins</hi> had alſo Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at <hi>Constantinople:</hi> Whence it was not poſſible, that being ſo mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137243:14"/>either of them could be ignorant of the Sentiments of one another, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in reſpect of a Myſtery; concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, there was riſen up a Hereſie in the Judgment at leaſt of the <hi>Latins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore it is inconceivable, that if the <hi>Greeks</hi> had been <hi>Berengarians</hi> at that time, (as Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> would have it believed) they ſhould have without the leaſt buſtle or noiſe, ſuffered the <hi>Latin</hi> Church to condemn as an Hereſie their Sentiment in the matter of the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist:</hi> And that the <hi>Latins</hi> on their ſide ſhould have ſaid nothing to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ſeeing them maintain that ſame Hereſie which they had ſo recently condemned in the perſon of <hi>Berengarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is certain that theſe two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches did not at that time, nor afterwards, upbraid one another on this matter; although they were never more incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor had greater provocations to have done it, if there had been any ground for it. For it was at that time there aroſe the hotteſt debate that could
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137243:15"/>be imagined, betwixt <hi>Michael Ceru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Acride,</hi> Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan of <hi>Bulgaria</hi> on one ſide, and Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> and the whole <hi>Latin</hi> Church, on the other. Nothing could parallel the bitterneſs and animoſity of the <hi>Greeks. Michael</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> of <hi>Acride</hi> did write in the year 1053, (which is the very ſame year wherein <hi>Berengarius</hi> was condemned in two Councils both held in <hi>Italy,</hi> one at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other at <hi>Vercelli</hi>) to <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Trani</hi> in <hi>Apulia.</hi> This Letter was moſt bitter: They upbraided the <hi>Latins</hi> in ſeveral things: <hi>That celebrating the</hi> Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt <hi>in</hi> Azimis, <hi>they communicated with the</hi> Jews: <hi>That they eated ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled meats: That they did not ſing</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluia <hi>in Lent:</hi> But not ſo much as one word of the Faith of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> And this Letter having been communicated to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the IX. He wrote thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Letter to that Patriarch and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, wherein after having defended
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137243:15"/>the <hi>Latin</hi> Church on the point of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimis,</hi> he complains of the violence of the Patriarch <hi>Michael,</hi> who had cauſed ſhut up all the Churches of the <hi>Latins</hi> that were at <hi>Constantinople:</hi> And he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols the modeſty of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, in that there being ſeveral Churches of the <hi>Greeks</hi> both within and without the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet they were not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to obſerve the Traditions of their Anceſtors. <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the</hi> Roman <hi>Church knows well that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Cuſtoms, according to Times and Places, is no ways prejudicial to the Salvation of Believers, when they have the Same Faith.</hi> Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that although there were then a great number of <hi>Greeks</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> whoſe Sentiments in matter of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> Pope <hi>Leo</hi> could not be ignorant of; he was perſwaded there was no more but <hi>a diverſity of Cuſtoms</hi> in point of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Azimis,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church; and that both theſe Churches had but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137243:16"/>one and the ſame Faith of that Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And conſequently he was no le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſwaded that the <hi>Greek</hi> Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> as well as the <hi>Latin:</hi> For a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not deny that ſhe believed both thoſe points at that time.</p>
               <p>This is farther confirmed by another Letter which <hi>Michael Cerularius</hi> wrote the year following (when he could be no more ignorant of the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Berengarius</hi>) to the Patriarch of <hi>Antiochia:</hi> which as the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is full of Accuſations againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, to perſwade him to forſake the Popes Communion; amongſt which Accuſations, there were ſome altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther calumnious, as that the <hi>Latins</hi> did not Honour St. <hi>Baſil</hi> and Sr. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom;</hi> and yet not ſo much as a word of their Belief of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which had been a far more conſiderable ground of ſeparation, if the <hi>Greeks</hi> had not had the ſame Faith on that matter, than the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137243:16"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifles which they objected to the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins: That their Prieſts raiſed their Beards: That their Monks eated fat: That their Biſhops carried the Effigies of a Lamb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by what paſſed at <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> betwixt Cardinal <hi>Humbertus,</hi> one of the moſt zealous Adverſaries of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius,</hi> whom <hi>Leo</hi> the IX. ſent thither to compoſe matters in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; and the <hi>Greeks</hi> whom <hi>Michael</hi> had exaſperated againſt the <hi>Latins.</hi> This Cardinal having there on ſeveral occaſions ſpoken ſo clearly of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> according to the Belief of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that it is impoſſible the <hi>Greeks</hi> did not underſtand him; or that they would have ſufferd him, if they had not had the ſame Faith.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, by the Council held at <hi>Placentia</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> in the year 1095, under <hi>Victor</hi> the II. where the <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Hereſie was again condemned, and the Catholich Faith declared in theſe terms: <hi>That the Bread and Wine being
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137243:17"/>conſecrated on the Altar, are changed not onely in figure, but abſolutely and eſſentially into the Body and Bloud of the Lord.</hi> Which cannot be ſaid to have been unknown to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of the Emperour <hi>Alexius Comnenus</hi> having been preſent at this Council. So that if the <hi>Greeks</hi> had not been of the ſame Faith with the <hi>Latins</hi> in that point, it's impoſſible but ſo ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing a deciſion would have ſtrangely ſtartled them; and in this aſtoniſhment made them advertiſe the Emperour and all <hi>Greece</hi> of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:137243:17"/>
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proof of the Minor as to the firſt time, that is, the Proof of the impoſſibility of an Innovation, whereof no memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remained, which the</hi> Calviniſts <hi>muſt ſay was made in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the World, from the end of the Ninth Age, to the beginning of the Eleventh. First member of this Proof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Major being proved in regard of the firſt time; that is to ſay, it being to be held for certain, that in the time of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> all the Churches of the Eaſt, eſpecially the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, had the ſame Faith of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which the <hi>Roman</hi> Church had; which the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> does not deny to have at that time believed the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> If it was not the ancient Faith of the Church, theſe Churches muſt have changed their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137243:18"/>of this Myſtery by an Innovation whereof themſelves were not ſenſible, nor did perceive, and of which no trace nor memory has remained perceivable to us: And this is what is ſaid to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, in the Firſt Part of the Minor of the famous Argument of the <hi>Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Calviniſts</hi> on the contrary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that this not only was not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but that it had <hi>de facto</hi> come to paſs by a Book of <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> a Monk of <hi>Corbie,</hi> made in the beginning of the Ninth Age. They accuſe him to have been an Innovator or Broacher of a new Doctrine, and to have been the firſt Author of <hi>Tranſubstantiation;</hi> they ſet up incontinently Adverſaries againſt him: But they ſuppoſe that this Book of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> and his Schollars who defended it, did inſenſibly corrupt the minds of a great many Men, and that this made ſuch a progreſs, during the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and darkneſs of the tenth Age, that thoſe of the Eleventh, tho' become more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137243:18"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lear-ſighted, having ſuckt in this opinion with their Milk, made it paſs for truth. <hi>Hinc contigit,</hi> ſays <hi>Aubertin,</hi> pag. 443. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut in ſequenti ſaeculo, quamvis literati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res facti, hac tamen opinione cum lacte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbuti, illam tanquàm veram confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obtruſerint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is what the Salvation of <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> is grounded upon: If this Romance be not true, there is no Salvation for them, becauſe there is none for thoſe who overturns or deſtroys in ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a matter, the ancient Faith of all the Chriſtians of the World, and who have taken the ſame Faith for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pretext of their ſchiſmatical ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Church.</p>
               <p>Now we have ſhewn in ſeveral places of the <hi>Books of the Perpetuity,</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there a Fable worſe contrived, though Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> thinks it the moſt exact and beſt invented that could be: <hi>For what is there</hi> (ſays he) <hi>more reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, than to ſay that</hi> Paſchaſius <hi>his Opinion, adorned with the Colours of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137243:19"/>Antiquity although in reality it was but a Novelty, ſupported with a little Philoſophy, extoll'd by theſe big words which ignorants admire, and propoſed in Ages like the Ninth and Tenth, did find at the beginning ſome Sectators, who induced others to follow them, until at laſt it became the strongeſt, and was eſtabliſhed by the aſſistance of violence and Authority</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But its his pleaſure, to the end he may render this Innovation leſs abſurd, never to repreſent it with thoſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, with which it muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have been accompanied, if it had fallen out.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that about the end of the Ninth Age, and the beginning of the Tenth, all the Biſhops, Prieſts, Monks, and <hi>Laicks,</hi> having been inſtructed in the Belief of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> (which ought to have been, according to the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> the common Belief of the Ninth Age) they abandoned without reſiſtance and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137243:19"/>without debate, the Faith of their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, to follow a new Opinion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by a Monk of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that this comes to paſs without noiſe or tumult.</p>
               <p>The third is, that this change is made at the ſame time, and after the ſame manner, in all the Churches of the World, it being, as we have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that they are all found to have been of the ſame Faith of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> in the beginning of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh Age.</p>
               <p>The fourth is, that no trace of this change remains; and the memory of it ſo aboliſht, that in the Eleventh Age immediately following that wherein they ſay that Innovation was made, no perſon had heard tell of it, as appears ſufficiently, in that there being in the year 1003, a Council held at <hi>Orleans, (Spicileg. Tom.</hi> 11. p. 675.) wherein were condemned as Hereticks, two Prieſts, for having denied amongſt other things, that the Bread is changed into
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137243:20"/>the Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe of theſe four circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the two laſt are they which ſhews more palpably the impoſſibility of this change, and are leaſt expoſed to be elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any wrangling; I ſhall content my ſelf to ſet down here, how theſe two circumſtances are preſſed in the Ninth Book of the Firſt Tome of the <hi>Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is treated of in the third Chapter, which has for Title, <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Engines of Retrenchment, or Means by which Mr.</hi> Claud <hi>exempts himſelf from making the Doctrine of the</hi> Real Preſence, <hi>preached to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of Chriſtians.</hi> And here is what is ſaid of it.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>How happy ſhould Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> be, if the Effects followed his Words, as his Words follows his Deſires; and if to make things true, it were enough that he aſſured them to be ſo, as it is enough for him to deſire them, for aſſuring
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137243:20"/>them! Then we ſhould eaſily ſee come to paſs that wonderful change he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undertakes to make in the Tenth Age: But the ill is, that the things which are without him, and thoſe by paſt Events, have an inflexible and unva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iable cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, which ſuits not at all with his Deſires: And ſo it falls out, that he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons of them on his ſide as he pleaſes himſelf; and on the other, the things remains ſtill quite contrary to what he ſays of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Queſtion,</hi> ſays he, p 641. <hi>is not of the whole-World; it's onely of the Occident, and of the Provinces ſubject to the Obedience of the Pope.</hi> That is to ſay, I will not have this to be the queſtion; I will not be at the pains to explicate, how the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was introduced in the Eaſt, in the Patriarchates of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia,</hi> in the Churches of the <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Nestorians, and Jacobites:</hi> I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:137243:21"/>will not trouble my ſelf to gueſs how it did penetrate into <hi>Ethiopia, Muſcovia, Meſopotamia, Georgia, Mingrelia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oldavia, Tartaria,</hi> and into the <hi>Ind a</hi>'s; I had better ſay it is not there, I will have ſooner done, and by this means I will free my ſelf of a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulties.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> if he pleaſes, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us to adverriſe him, that he is Man, and nor God; and conſequently nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Words nor his Wiſhes are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. He would not have the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> to be in all theſe great Provinces: But it is and will be in them, whether he would or would not, the matter does not at all depend upon him: And we have made it appear by Proofs, which we judge himſelf will not gainſtand.</p>
                  <p>So that notwithſtanding of all his Wiſhes, the queſtion is to know how the belief of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> could be introduced in all theſe places, if it had not ſtill been in them. Cerrain it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137243:21"/>is, that it is there eſtabliſhed, and reigns and domineers abſolutely. There is no other known, no memory that ever any other Doctrine was there. All theſe Nations are perſwaded they hold it by continual ſucceſſion from their Forefathers It is manifeſt they have held always this Doctrine, ſince the time the <hi>Berengarians</hi> were firſt heard of; and that in this point they were ſtill united with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> muſt then tell us, who has made them embrace this Doctrine: But how can he do it, ſince the reaſon why he would exeem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from entring into this queſtion, is, becauſe he finds that not only ſolid Proofs, but even Inventions and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions fails him; all his Machines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come uſeleſs to him. He talks to us of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> of Diſputes, of the Intrigues of Monks, of the Violences of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> And to render all this heap of Dreams and Viſions ridiculous, there needs no more but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:137243:22"/>to oblige him to caſt his eyes on two third parts of the World, which knows neither <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> nor his Book; and are ſo far from acknowledging the Pope, that they are moſt paſſionately bent to contradict him in all they can.</p>
                  <p>Let Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> tell us therefore, who did perſwade them to a Belief which he pretends to be directly contrary to Scripture, to Fathers, to Reaſon and Senſe? What Preachers did produce ſo great an effect? How comes it to paſs that none of all theſe Nations did reſiſt this Innovation? How comes it to paſs that all of them have forgot they changed their Perſwaſion, and takes their preſent Doctrine for that which the Apoſtles eſtabliſhed in the Church, and which has deſcended even to them by the ſucceſſion of their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
                  <p>Mr.
<note place="margin">See pag. 2. of the General Anſwer.</note> 
                     <hi>Claud</hi> wearies his Imagination to invent an impertinent Fable of a young
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:137243:22"/>Monk, who without going out of his Convent, and without being heard tell of abroad, yet changes the Faith of the whole Occident: He torments him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to accompany this Fable with a thouſand phantaſtical ſuppoſitions: He exhauſts all his Figures, and all his big Words, to dazle a little the eyes of the ſimple; and to hide from them the abſurdity of this Romance.</p>
                  <p>But he takes no heed that all his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours are in vain; there remains more than two thirds of his Work to be done; without which, all the pains he takes are to no purpoſe; he muſt yet find other <hi>Paſchaſius</hi>'s to carry this Faith into all the Societies ſeparate from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Provinces: All theſe <hi>Paſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>'s muſt have the ſame ſucceſs, that no perſon contradict nor oppoſe their Enterprizes; that no perſon perceive them renverſing the ancient Faith; and in a word, they muſt all have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht their work at the ſame time,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:137243:23"/>when <hi>Berengarius</hi> ſhall happen to ſtart up, to the end he might with ſome ground of reaſon ſay, <hi>That the Church was periſhed, and there was no more remnant of it than thoſe who followed him</hi> (Lanfrancus, cap. 23.)</p>
                  <p>I ſee very well that Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> for all his ſtoutneſs, ſuccumbs under the greatneſs of this Enterprize: It frights him, he gives it over, he asks pardon, he would wiſh with all his heart, that that this made no part of the Queſtion. <hi>The Queſtion</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is not of all the World.</hi> But there is no moyen to be complaiſant to him: The Queſtion is of the whole World, whether he will or will not becauſe that Belief is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht throughout the World. This depends neither upon him nor me: It is a neceſſary part of this great Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which draws all the reſt after it. Wherefore ſince by a conſtrained confeſſion of his inability, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he cannot ſay there was made an univerſal change of Belief in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:137243:23"/>whole Orient, he muſt needs abandon all the reſt, and avow that all his moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens are ruined, all his Engines ſhatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all his Projects renverſed, and all his Suppoſitions deſtroyed.</p>
                  <p>If he ſay it was <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented this Doctrine, and that it could never have fallen into the brain of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we ſhew him an infinite number of Chriſtians, who neither knows <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius,</hi> nor his Book, and who yet makes ſtill profeſſion of this Doctrine; and here he is convinced of timerity and impoſture.</p>
                  <p>If he tells us, <hi>That the Popes did by their Authority and Violences, concur to make it be received;</hi> We ſhall let him ſee thoſe great Nations, over whom they have no Juriſdiction, in which they are not acknowledged, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom their Deciſions have neither Credit nor Authority; and who notwithſtanding are no leſs tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of the Faith of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> as thoſe People who are moſt ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:137243:24"/>to the Holy See; and this does far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point him out as a Deceiver of the World, by groundleſs and improbable Fables.</p>
                  <p>If he talks to us of Cabals and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Intrigues, of Diſputes of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, by which he pretends this Doctrine was eſtabliſhed; we ſhall ſhew an infinite number of People, who neither knows the School Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, nor never diſputed of theſe matters; and amongſt whom even the imagination of Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> himſelf could never make the Intrigues of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> active; and who yet believes the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> as we do: And lo here alſo all his Reckonings and Fables annihilated.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This is what regards the third Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance; which is, that this Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould have been made at the ſame time in all the Churches of the World: Which renders it ſo evidently impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> could not extricate himſelf otherwiſe (as we have ſhewn)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:137243:24"/>than by an Engine or <hi>Machine of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>renchment,</hi> whereby he would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s believe, againſt all truth, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oint controverted in this matter, is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he belief of the whole World, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y that of the Occident, and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces ſubmitted to the Obedience of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Pope.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:137243:25"/>
               <head>SECT. 5 </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Member of the Proo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the impoſſibility of an inſenſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> change, from the end of the Ninth Age, to the beginning of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe fourth Circumſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Innovation ought to have been made in a manner ſo imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible, as that no tract thereof remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to poſterity, is treated in the ninth Chapter of the ſame Book, which has for Title, <hi>Examination of the Engines or Means of Execution, in which is ſhewn the impoſſibility of an inſenſible change.</hi> I would wiſh one ſhould read it entirely, for they would have greater ſatisfaction: But not to be too prolix, I ſhall tranſcribe here the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:137243:25"/>
                  <p>The inutility of the preceeding means made uſe of by Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> gives us no ground to expect great matter from thoſe he pretends were made uſe of to bring to paſs this inſenſible change. So it may be ſeen in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription thereof, made on his own proper words, that he knows not what to lay hold on, and employs contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory means. Sometimes he makes the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> eſtabliſht <hi>by the noiſe of Diſputes,</hi> pag. 300. Sometimes he avows there were no Diſputes in the Tenth Age, in which he pretends this change was made, <hi>pag.</hi> 651. So here we have right to ask of him in the firſt place, that he would take his option; and that in chuſing one of theſe chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical moyens he ſhould confeſs he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced the other falſly and timerari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
                  <p>Yet it muſt be granted, that if the contradiction be evident, it is in ſome manner neceſſary; and he was forced to it by the conſequence of his falſe
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:137243:26"/>it was impoſſible the Belief of the <hi>Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Preſence</hi> ſhould be introduced into the Church, in caſe it had not always been in it, without a great number of Diſputes and Conteſtations; and therefore at firſt he lays hold on this moyen, as abſolutely neceſſary for his purpoſe. <hi>Theſe Meanings or Senſes,</hi> ſays he, <hi>were aſſaulted by the noiſe of Diſputes,</hi> pag. 30. But when he ſaw that theſe Diſputes did neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily draw after them Writings on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, and that he could produce none; he repents himſelf of the ſtep he had advanced, and retires back in contradicting himſelf by a pretty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titheſe as we have ſeen: <hi>I conclude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</hi> ſays he, <hi>pag.</hi> 400. <hi>that ſince there were no Writings on the matter, there were no Diſputes about it. The conſequence in my opinion is reaſonable; but I do not conclude, that there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been no Diſputes, therefore the Doctrine of the Church was not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted. The conſequence is not good;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:137243:26"/>was establiſhed without being defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. ......... I conclude indeed, that if there had been Diſputes on the point, Ignorance had not ſubſiſted: But I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude likewiſe, that Ignorance has ſubſiſted, becauſe there were no Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we require proofs from Mr. <hi>Claud.</hi> that the <hi>Real Abſence</hi> (which he calls the Doctrine of the Church) was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted <hi>by falſe Philoſophy, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of Monks, and hy the Authority of the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more fierce nor more powerful.</hi> He would be no leſs ſtraitned than he is, to produce Writings and Diſputes; for there is as little likelihood in the one as the other. Never was there any thing more remote from Philoſophy true or falſe, than all what remains of the Writings of the Tenth Age: And if there was any ignorance greater in this than in other Ages, it was onely of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Philoſophy, and Humane Literature: For the Eccleſiaſticks of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:137243:27"/>that time, applied themſelves onely to the reading of the holy Scripture and the Fathers.</p>
                  <p>That Authority of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> ſays <hi>was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fierce nor ſo powerful,</hi> and by which he will have the true Doctrine to have been attacked, is alſo a fiction not only timeratious and groundleſs, but notoriouſly falſe, and contrary to the truth of Hiſtory: For not onely the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> was neither fierce nor powerful in the Tenth Age, but was extreamly depreſſed; for the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours taking upon them to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Popes, and elect others; it may be ſaid, that during all this Age, the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence of the Temporal Power, and conſequently was never leſs in conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make a new Doctrine be recevied by the whole Church, as it was never farther from enterprizing it.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Intrigues of Monks are meer fables, without likelihood and without
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:137243:27"/>ground. The Monks of theſe times were either diſorderly and thought little on, changing the Faith of the Church; or reformed, as theſe of the Congregation of <hi>Cluny,</hi> the <hi>Camaldu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſes</hi> eſtabliſht by St. <hi>Romuald</hi> in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the Monks of <hi>Germany</hi> reformed by the Biſhops. There were alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Reforms made in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> of which mention is made in the Book of the <hi>Perpetuity:</hi> But all theſe Reforms aimed at the withdrawing of the Monks from the Intrigues of the World, and not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle them therein. We have yet extant the Life of St. <hi>Mayeul,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by St. <hi>Odilon,</hi> that of St. <hi>Odo</hi> written by an Author contemporary; thoſe of St. <hi>Odilon</hi> and St. <hi>Romuald,</hi> written by <hi>Petrus Damianus.</hi> As all theſe perſons were perſwaded of the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> St. <hi>Odo</hi> ſpeaks honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> in his Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; St <hi>Odo</hi> ſaw <hi>Berengarius, Petrus Damianus</hi> ſurvived the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:137243:28"/>of his Hereſie, and condemns it every where throughout all his Books; ſo they would have made no difficulty to avow, that they whoſe Lives they wrote, had laboured to eſtabliſh the Belief of the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi> They would have thought Intrigues for ſuch a ſubject honourable; and taking from them the name of Intrigues, they would have made them paſs for works of their Zeal for the Truth.</p>
                  <p>And yet we find not that it's obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of any of theſe holy religious Men, that they contributed any manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> way to root out the Opinion contrary to the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> nor to ſpread that Doctrine abroad.</p>
                  <p>I knew not if Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> has been at the pains to reflect on this Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if he ſees the conſequence that ſprings from it. So that to help him to draw them, I entreat him to conſider, that if it was true that the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> had been eſtabliſht in the Tenth Age, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:137243:28"/>pagated into all the Provinces of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom. It muſt be abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that all thoſe who were repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Piety and Learning in theſe times, had their part in its eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and laboured for the ſame. And as there can hardly be imagined a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter work, than to perſwade this Belief to all the Eccleſiaſticks, and to all the People, to overcome all the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Reaſon and their Senſes, fortified by the multitude, and by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſtomed to other more eaſie and more humane Cogitations: It would have doubtleſs been the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Occupation of theſe <hi>Paſchaſites;</hi> and theſe <hi>Paſchaſites</hi> who ſhould have ſo changed the Faith of the whole Church, could be no other than Men who were conſidered as the Heads of the Religion of that Age, and who by their Authority drew the Eccleſiaſticks and People after them.</p>
                  <p>Now we have the Lives of the moſt part of theſe perſons, written by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:137243:29"/>contemporary, or at leaſt of the following Age.</p>
                  <p>We can reckon more than twenty of them (whom I omit for brevity) and reſume the Diſcourſe by this reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>But it is not ſaid neither of theſe Saints, nor of any other, that they preached the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> that they were zealous for its eſtabliſhment; that they converted many perſons to this Belief: And that which ſhould have been their chiefeſt occupation, and the principal object of their Zeal and Devotion, according to Mr. <hi>Clauld</hi>'s fancies, is not ſo much as obſerved by the Hiſtorians, ſave only by St. <hi>Odo</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> Uncle to St. <hi>Oſwald;</hi> but in a manner far from giving ground to think that the Belief of the <hi>Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> was not that of his time. The Hiſtory of St. <hi>Odo,</hi> which <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury</hi> draws from <hi>Osborn,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries onely that ſeveral perſons doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:137243:29"/>of the verity of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> he confirmed them in the Faith by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, in ſhewing the Hoſt changed into Fleſh. <hi>Plurimos de veritate Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minici corporis dubitantes,</hi> ſays <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury, it a roboravit, ut panem Altaris ver ſum in carnem, &amp; v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>num calicis in ſanguinem, propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam ostenderet, &amp; denuo in priſtinam ſpeciem retorta, uſui humano conduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia faceret,</hi> Guil Malmsb. <hi>in</hi> Odone. The matter of fact is acknowledged by the Proteſtants themſelves, though <hi>Baleus</hi> no leſs than <hi>Aubertin</hi> aſcribes it to the Devil, <hi>mendacibus Satanae miraculis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This proves indeed that there were in St. <hi>Odo</hi>'s time, ſome perſons who doubted of the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> which is no ſtrange thing, being that the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryitſelf is capable to excite theſe kind of doubts: And beſides this, <hi>John Scot</hi> had retired himſelf to <hi>England,</hi> where he might have made ſome private Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of his Doctrine.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:137243:30"/>
                  <p> But here its manifeſtly ſeen, that this doubt was condemned by <hi>Odo,</hi> Head of the Engliſh Church; who having been lookt upon as a Saint by thoſe of his time, and not accuſed of Errour by any, is an unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Witneſs of the Faith of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> during the Tenth Age</p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Osborn</hi> in the Life of St. <hi>Dunſtan,</hi> chap. 44. ſpeaks likewiſe of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> but onely occaſionally, and to ſhew how much this Saint was repleniſhed with the Spirit of God: <hi>Being returned,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to the Altar, he changed the Bread and Wine into the Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>by the holy Benediction: And when he had given the Bleſſing to the People, he left once more the Altar to preach; and being inebriated with the Spirit of God, he ſpake of the verity of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>of the future Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and of Life eternal, in ſuch a manner, that one would have thought
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:137243:30"/>they heard ſpeaking a Man already beatified.</hi> Lo here the rank which was given to the Article of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> in the Tenth Age.</p>
                  <p>It ought moreover to be concluded from the example of St. <hi>Odo,</hi> that if all the Authors of the Lives of Saints had had any ſuch thing to be related of thoſe whoſe Lives they wrote, and if they had had ground to remark the Converſions they had made, they would not have omitted to have done it; and conſequently their ſilence is an evident proof, that theſe Saints never had it in their view to inſpire the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> that they never dream'd of this project: And as it could not have been eſtabliſhed by others than by them, it follows that it was not eſtabliſhed by any perſon in that Age, becauſe it needed not, being the ancient Belief of preceeding Ages.</p>
               </q>
               <p>After having remarked what ought to have been found in the Lives writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten particularly of the Saints of that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:137243:31"/>time, we paſs next to the Hiſtories, Annals, and Chronicles.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The ſame obſervation may be made on the Hiſtorian <hi>Ditmarus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mersbourg,</hi> who at leaſt had no leſs intention to write the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory of his time, than that of the Temporal State of <hi>Germany:</hi> His great Birth did not ſuffer him to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what paſſed in his time: He was an intimate Friend of all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of his Age; and he makes the Eloge of ſeveral of them in his Hiſtory, wherein are reckoned to the number of eleven: He ſpeaks of a great many others, and makes his own Life in his Hiſtory; but he neither mentions of himſelf, nor of any other that took pains to eſtabliſh the Belief of the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Will Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> ſay that all theſe Biſhops had no part in this Work, or that the matter was not worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marking? Will he pretend that to withdraw <hi>Germany</hi> from an Opinion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:137243:31"/>which the <hi>Paſchaſites</hi> muſt have lookt upon as a deteſtable Crime, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World a Doctrine ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Reaſon; and which they judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo neceſſary for Salvation, was a thing too trivial to appear in the Eloge of theſe Biſhops?</p>
                  <p>We find the ſame ſilence in all the other Hiſtorians of the Ninth and Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th Age, how ſollicitous ſoever they were to tranſmit to us the Affairs of the Church. There are reckoned up ten, what Hiſtories, what Annals or Chronicles, which ſays not ſo much as one word of that eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> of theſe Diſputes, of theſe Converſions, nor of the Zeal of the Biſhops of that time, to inſtruct all the people in that Doctrine,</p>
                  <p>In a word, as Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> who is acute enough to forſee what ought to be, miſſes not to rank amongſt thoſe means which could advance the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the <hi>Real Preſence, the Intrigues of Courts, the Combinations
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:137243:32"/>of great Men, the Intereſts of Biſhops and other worldly Engines;</hi> and which he ſays he would <hi>have remarked, if he had been living at that time:</hi> It muſt be granted to him, that Intrigues which ſhould have had ſo great effects, ought to have been moſt remarkable; and yet we find no mention at all made of them, in any of the contemporary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, who wrote the Lives of the Princes and Princeſſes of this Age, as in <hi>Wittichindus, Ditmarus, Glaber, Rodolphus, Helgaldus, Odilo,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others. Many proofs are there ſeen of the Zeal of theſe two Princes for Religion; and it's hard to find any who were more careful, who had more favour for the Church, and who had more eſteem and affection for the holy Biſhops and Religious Men of their time. And if it was true that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> was intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in their time, it muſt have been by their Authority and favour. Whence comes it then, that that Zeal, and all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:137243:32"/>theſe Actions which ſhould have flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it, have not been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by any Author: And that in the telling us of theſe Kings, of theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Princeſſes, they make no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their particular Devotion to the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> nor of the care they had to eſtabliſh it more and more among the faithful.</p>
               </q>
               <p>And yet according to Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> theſe Princes ought to have had a great hand in that Innovation, no leſs than the Pope and the Biſhops, ſeeing that to make it the more credible, he ſuppoſes <hi>Paſcaſius</hi> his Doctrine, ought to have been eſtabliſht by the help of Violence and Authority. But it was found alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether eſtabliſhed then, when <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> propoſed his figurative Sence: So there muſt have been before <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> either Princes or Popes, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, who employed Violence or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to ſet it in that height of credit it was found in before <hi>Berengarius</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared. How comes it then, that in ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:137243:33"/>many Hiſtories, Annals, and Lives of holy Biſhops, nothing of all that is to be ſeen.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The prodigious ſilence of ſo many perſons, on a matter ſo important as the univerſal change of Belief, which could no have come to paſs, without the participation of all theſe he ſpeaks of, will ſtand for a moſt evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration to all judicious perſons; there being no method more convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to prove Negatives of this kind; for it ought not to be pretended, that theſe Authors ſhould have propheſied, that there were to come Men ſo auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious as to aſſert that the whole Church had changed her Faith during this Age, or that they were obliged to belye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand ſo ridiculous an Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I pretend then that the Minor is moſt clearly proved in reſpect of the firſt time; that is to ſay, the impoſſibility of a change, whereof no trace ſhould have remained, which the <hi>Calvinists</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:137243:33"/>muſt pretend to have been made in all the Churches of the World, from the end of the Ninth, to the beginning of the Eleventh Age, is moſt ſolidly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated. There remains then no more but to prove the ſecond part of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor; that is, the unanimous agreement of all theſe Churches at this preſent time.</p>
               <p>And the ſecond part of the Minor, to wit, That it's impoſſible they ſhould be found at preſent in this union, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible change as to the Faith of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which ſhould have hapned in all the Churches of the Eaſt, in the time that has run ſince <hi>Berengarius</hi> till now. And this is a thing more eaſie, becauſe the truth of things nearer to us is diſcovered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:137243:34"/>
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proofs of the Major in regard of the preſent time; that is to ſay, that the Eaſtern Churches, eſpecially the</hi> Greek <hi>Church, are of the ſame Faith that the</hi> Roman <hi>Church is concerning the</hi> Euchariſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Cannot tell if ever there was a matter of fact proved by ſo many pieces and irrefragable Teſtimonies, as the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent Eaſtern Church with the <hi>Roman,</hi> in the Belief of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that is, of the <hi>Real Preſence, Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and <hi>Adoration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are all to be ſeen, ſome in the Firſt <hi>Tome</hi> of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> Book 12. others in the firſt Book of the General Anſwer; and more at length in the Thrid Tome, Book 8. Where they are found altogether marked at the end in a Table which here follows.</p>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:137243:34"/>
                  <head>For the <hi>Greek</hi> Church of the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Writing of a Nobleman of <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davia,</hi> concerning the Belief of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> entituled, <hi>Enchiridion, ſive ſtella Orientalis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Letter of M. <hi>Olarius,</hi> concerning the Belief of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extract of a Synod held in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> in the year 1668.</p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of a Prieſt and Canon of <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> and of three other <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites</hi> in the Ambaſſadors Train, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Belief of their Nation.</p>
                  <p>Confeſſion of Faith required by <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodius</hi> from Doctor <hi>Cicada.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extract of the Book of <hi>Agapius,</hi> Monk of Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> entituled, <hi>The Salvation of Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of eight Superiors and Monks of Mount <hi>Athos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:137243:35"/>
                  <p> Atteſtation of <hi>Methodius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtarion of the Superior of Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> concerning <hi>Agapius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of ſeven Archbiſhops of the Eaſt.</p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Church of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fland of <hi>Anaxia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Church of the Iſles of <hi>Cephalonia, Zacynthus,</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaca.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Iſle of <hi>Micone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Iſle of <hi>Milo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Church of the Iſle of <hi>Chios.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of a Superiour and the Monks of the Monaſtery of <hi>Mauro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Letter of M. <hi>Panjotti.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> of three other Patriarchs preceeding him, and of the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans of that Patriarchate</p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Churches of <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grelia, Colichis,</hi> and <hi>Georgia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:137243:35"/>
                  <p> Atteſtation of the Vicar Apoſtolick, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſident at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of M. <hi>Caſimir,</hi> Reſident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <hi>Poland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of M. <hi>Quirino,</hi> Refident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the Republick of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of M. <hi>Fieſchi,</hi> Reſident of <hi>Genoa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Ambaſſadors of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he the Republick of <hi>Raguſa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Community of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Perots, as well Supetiours as Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers.</p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of M. <hi>Taiſia,</hi> on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eath of his Son, communicated by the <hi>Greeks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extract of ſome Deciſions of the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſent to the <hi>Ruſſians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Anſwer of <hi>Marcus Donus</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Iſle of <hi>Candia,</hi> ſent to Mr. <hi>Claud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Monaſtery of St. <hi>George.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extract of the Treatiſe of <hi>Meletius Syrigus,</hi> againſt <hi>Cyrilius Lucar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="proof">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:137243:36"/>
                  <head>For the <hi>Greek</hi> Church of the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Extract of a Letter of the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ſent to <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <head>For the <hi>Greek</hi> Church of the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate of <hi>Antiochia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Profeſſion of the Faith of the <hi>Greek</hi> of the Patriarchate of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Condemnation of the <hi>Calvinists</hi> by <hi>Macarius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Greek</hi> Nation.</p>
                  <p>A new Condemnation of the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> by the Grecian Church of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchate of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> under the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch <hi>Neophilus,</hi> ſigned by the Patriarch Archbiſhops, Curats, Prieſts, Deacons and others.</p>
                  <p>Apology of <hi>Sotericus Panteugen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to the Patriarch of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Council, concerning the matters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which he was accuſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:137243:36"/>
                  <head>For the <hi>Grecian</hi> Church of the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Letter of <hi>Nectarius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> to <hi>Payſius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xandria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extract of a Synodical Treatiſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Docitheus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> and by a Synod at the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> ſigned by ſixty two Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Curats and other Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks.</p>
                  <p>Extract of the Treatiſe of <hi>Elias</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> concerning the Myſteries, drawn from an Arabick Manuſcript of the Kings <hi>Bibliotheck.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <head>For the four Patriarchs together.</head>
                  <p>A Book entituled, <hi>The Orthodox Confeſſion of the Oriental Church,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the four Patriarchs.</p>
                  <p>Approbation of the ſecond Edition of the ſame Book.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proof">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:137243:37"/>
                  <head>For the Maronites.</head>
                  <p>Act or Treatiſe of the <hi>Marionites</hi> of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> concerning the Faith of their Churches.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <head>For the Armenian Church.</head>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the <hi>Armenian</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, who is preſently at <hi>Rome,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the of Belief the <hi>Armenians</hi> in matter of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſcanus</hi> Biſhop of St. <hi>Sergius</hi> in the Greater <hi>Armenia,</hi> given at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Patriarch and of ſeveral Prieſts and <hi>Armenian</hi> Biſhops reſiding at <hi>Alippo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Patriarch of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meazin,</hi> concerning the Belief of the <hi>Armenians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the <hi>Armenian</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> of <hi>Amaſea,</hi> and <hi>Adrinople.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:137243:37"/>
                  <p> Atteſtation of the Patriarch of <hi>Cis,</hi> at number 10.</p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the <hi>Armenians</hi> of <hi>Cairo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the <hi>Armenians</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pahan</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> at number 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <head>For the Church of the Syrians.</head>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Patriarch of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> concerning the Faith of their Churches, in matter of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>Condemnation of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> by the Church of the <hi>Syrians</hi> at <hi>Damaſcus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extract of an Arabick Manuſcript of the Kings <hi>Bibliotheck,</hi> ſhewing the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the <hi>Jacobites</hi> concerning the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist,</hi> in the Tenth Age.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <head>For the Neſtorians.</head>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Patriarch of the <hi>Nestorians</hi> of the Town of <hi>Diabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:137243:38"/>
                  <p> Extract out of the Miſſals and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-Books of the <hi>Neſtorians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <head>For the Church of Cophtes.</head>
                  <p>Atteſtation of the Patriarch of the <hi>Cophtes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another Atteſtation of the ſame, concetning the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> In particular.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Atteſtations are to be found at the end of the Third Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity of the Faith,</hi> either at length or by citation of other places of theſe Books.</p>
                  <p>I know not if Mr. <hi>Sphanhemius,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor at <hi>Leyden,</hi> will yet be ſo bold as to ſay, as he did in his <hi>Strictures</hi> againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Book, that no regard is to be had to all theſe Atteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as being given <hi>by the miſerable</hi> Greeks, <hi>who can be made to ſay any thing one pleaſes for Money: A quibus nihil non pretio extorqueas.</hi> And ſo we have ground to think, that they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:137243:38"/>ſtill in the Opinion of the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> concerning the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> even when they ſeem to condemn it with the greateſt zeal. But I perſwade my ſelf there is no honeſt man but will conceive indignation at an Anſwer ſo unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which leaves us no moyen to be aſſured of the Religion of any People. The leaſt that thoſe deſerves who makes uſe of it, is to doubt whether they be <hi>Chriſtians, Jews,</hi> or <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans;</hi> there being left them no way to hinder us from believing that they are in their heart any thing we pleaſe to ſuſpect them of.</p>
                  <p>But to deprive them of all means of being able by their moſt unjuſt and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Calumnies, to brangle thoſe who ſhall read this little Treatiſe, I ſhall chuſe one only of all theſe Teſtimonies, which is the Book of the <hi>Orthodox Confeſſion,</hi> whereof the Hiſtory is ſet down in the General Anſwer, Book 1. Chap. 9. in theſe terms.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:137243:39"/>
                     <p>If one ſhould ſet himſelf on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to contrive the Idea of an Act proper to decide the matter in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt us, he could not in my Judgment require other conditions, and other circumſtances than thoſe I am going to ſpeak of.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That it be ſigned and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the four Patriarchs, and by the principal Biſhops and Eccleſiaſticks of the Eaſtern Church.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That it appear, that thoſe who made and approved it, had not any intelligence with the <hi>Latins,</hi> and that they continue in all the particular Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That it was made for the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular neceſſities of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, without that the <hi>Latins</hi> had any hand in it.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That the terms thereof be perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory, and contain ſo clearly the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubstantiation,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> cannot elude them by his ordinary ſubtilties.</p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:137243:39"/>
                     <p> Now all theſe circumſtances are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly found in the Act which I ſhall here ſet down, whereof a Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> named <hi>Nectarius,</hi> has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the pains to make the Hiſtory in a Letter at the beginning of it, and here it is.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peter Mogilas</hi> who had been ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Archbiſhop of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> by <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> having aſſembled three of the moſt Learned Biſhops his ſuffragants, and the moſt pious Theologues of his Archipiſcopal City, to baniſh away the Errours and Superſtitions of his People, reſolved with them by unanimous conſent, to draw up a Confeſſion of Faith, on the Articles of the Chriſtian Doctrine, and to cauſe it be received and approved by the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and by the Synod which was there aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
                     <p>To bring this to paſs they compoſed a Book on the Articles of Faith, which they entituled, <hi>The Confeſſion of Faith
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:137243:40"/>of the Ruſſians.</hi> And then they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to appoint thoſe they ſhould depute in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moldavia</hi> in quality of <hi>Exarcks,</hi> to examine it together with thoſe whom they ſhould ſend on their ſide.</p>
                     <p>The matter was executed as it was thus projected. The Synod of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> did depute into <hi>Moldavia Porphyrius</hi> Metropolitan of <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Meletius Syrigus</hi> Theologue of the Great Church; to whoſe Piety and Learning, the Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> gives very ample commendation: And the Deputies of the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> being met there, that Confeſſion of Faith was examined with all exactneſs poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     <p>But yet they did not content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with this examination, and to render this piece more Authentick, they thought fit to ſend it to all the four Patriarchs of the Eaſtern Church, and to ſubmit it anew to their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:137243:40"/>
                     <p> Theſe Patriarchs then having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and examined it, found it ſo conform to the Belief of their Church, that not onely they approved it, and ſigned it with their own hands, with many other Biſhops, but they appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moreover, that inſtead of the Title it had before of <hi>Confeſſion of Faith of the Ruſſians,</hi> it ſhould be thenceforth called, <hi>Confeſſion of Faith of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Orthodox Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>After the Letter of this Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> containing the Hiſtory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-mentioned, we find at the very beginning of that Confeſſion, the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and Subſcription of four Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, of nine Biſhops, and of all the principal Officers of the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Approbation of the four Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, is dated in the year 1643, in the Month of <hi>March,</hi> and that of the Letter of the Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was prefixed only to the Print is only in 1662. This Confeſſion no,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:137243:41"/>having been printed in <hi>Greek</hi> till long time after it was made, and not being diſtributed before but in writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> becauſe the <hi>Turks</hi> permits no Printing in their Empire.</p>
                     <p>As to all the other Conditions we have pointed at, they are likewiſe found in that Confeſſion.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Latins</hi> medled not in it any manner of way; it was allenerly made for the utility of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church. It was compoſed by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by all the Heads of the Eſtern Church: Theſe who compoſed it had no aim to gratifie any perſon.</p>
                     <p>It is now more than fourty years ſince it was made and more than twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſince it was printed.</p>
                     <p>Yea it appears the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were employed for the printing of it, for certainly the Types are of <hi>Holland.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All the Doctrines controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latins</hi> are therein openly aſſerted, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of this Confeſſion can be no ways
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:137243:41"/>ſuſpected to have had any ſway or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
                     <p>So that it's hard to imagine or deny a Book leſs ſuſpect, more authorized, more authentick, and of which greater aſſurance can be had that it contains the true Sentiments of the Eaſtern Church.</p>
                     <p>There remains no more but to ſee what it contains: And in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it begins to explain what regards the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:137243:42"/>
                  <head>QUESTION 106. <hi>Which is the third Sacrament?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IT is the holy</hi> Euchariſt; <hi>that is, the Body and Blood of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>under the appearances of Bread and Wine,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein truly, properly, and really preſent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here is enough for any other than Mr. <hi>Claud.</hi> But that he may not toil his mind to ſeek here ſome evaſion, I beſeech him to hear what is read in the following Interogation, it concerns the Conditions neceſſary for the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of this Myſtery, and it has theſe expreſs terms: <hi>In the fourth place, the Prieſt muſt be perſwaded, that at the time when he conſecrates the holy Gifts, the ſubſtance of the Bread, and the ſubſtance Wine, is changed into the ſubstance of the True
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:137243:42"/>Body and of the True Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>by the operation of the Holy Ghost, who is invocated at that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here is already theſe myſterious words; without which, Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> thinks the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, nor <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> and with which he muſt then avow that it is moſt formally expreſſed: For him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf grants, that the word <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> is not neceſſary when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is thus explained: But yet if he will require farther that we let him ſee the <hi>Greek</hi> Church uſing and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing it, he may be ſatisfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the following words.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>After the words of Inovocation, at the ſame inſtant</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) <hi>is made, and the Bread is changed into the True Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and the Wine into his True Blood, the appearances of the Bread and Wine remaining by a divine Oeconomy. Firſt that we may not ſee the Body of</hi>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:137243:43"/>Jeſus Chriſt <hi>with our Eyes but by Faith in leaning on thoſe words.</hi> This is my Body, this is my Blood; <hi>and by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we may prefer his Words and his Power, to our own Senſes; which acquires the beatitude of Faith, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what is ſaid,</hi> Bleſſed are thoſe who have not ſeen, and yet have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly, That becauſe Humane Nature has horrour to eat raw fleſh; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> that ſeeing we ought to be united to</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>by the participation of his Body and Blood, that Man might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> have averſion from it. God has provided for this Inconvenient, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to Believers his proper Fleſh and and Blood, under the vails of Bread and Wine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There remains no more to condemn the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> but to determine that this Sacrament ought to be adored with the ſame Honour that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is worſhipped, that is to ſay, <hi>Latria,</hi> and that it is a true Sacrifice; and theſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:137243:43"/>are ſeen in that Confeſſion, in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding terms:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Honour you ought to render to theſe dreadful Myſteries, ought to be the ſame which you render to</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>himſelf: So that as St.</hi> Peter <hi>ſpeaking for all the Apostles, ſaid to</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, Thou art Chriſt, the Son of the Living God; <hi>ſo every one of us worſhipping with</hi> Latria <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Worſhip theſe Myſteries, ought to ſay,</hi> I believe, Lord, and confeſs that you are the Chriſt the Son of the Living God, who came to the World to ſave Sinners, of whom I am the chief.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, this Myſtery is offered in Sacrifice for the Orthodox Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, both Living and Dead, in hope of the Reſurrection to Life eternal.</p>
                     <p>And a little after: <hi>This Myſtery is propitiatory before God, both for the Living and the Dead.</hi> The clearneſs of theſe Words, ſuppreſſes all reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:137243:44"/>which could do no more but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure it</p>
                     <p>Hitherto is what was ſaid in the year 1671. But whereas it was thought then by the Characters, that this Book had been printed in <hi>Holland,</hi> it was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards known to be certain; and we have learned the Hiſtory of it from M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Nointel,</hi> Ambaſſadour of <hi>France</hi> at the Port, who writ to <hi>Paris</hi> in theſe terms the year 1672 as is to be ſeen in the Third Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> Book 8. Chap 14.</p>
                     <p>The 15th of <hi>February</hi> one of my Friends has told me, that having di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with M. the Reſident of <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Diſcourſe falling upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> mention was made of the Book entituled, <hi>The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Confeſſion of the Catholick and Apoſtolick Church of the Eaſt,</hi> as ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying her Belief of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>M. the Reſident Diſcourſed of the origine of the printing of this Book;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:137243:44"/>for he told him that M <hi>Panajotti</hi> having ſent the Copy into <hi>Holland</hi> to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there on his expences, the States would not let his Money be taken; but to gain his favour, had cauſed moſt carefully to print it on their own Charges; and had entruſted ſeveral Boxes of the Impreſſion to their Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to be made a preſent to M. <hi>Pana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jotti.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The fourth of <hi>March</hi> I ordered <hi>Fontain</hi> to go to M. the Reſident of <hi>Holland,</hi> to thank him for what he had ſent me by his Secretaty, before his Voyage to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and to offer him his Services at the Port whither I was diſpatching him. He entreated him that he would do me the favour to give me one of theſe Books, entituled, <hi>The Orthodox Confeſſion of the Catholick and Apoſtolick Church of the East:</hi> And to let me know how it was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by what means ſome of the Copies thereof had come to his hands. The Reſident having teſtified how ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:137243:45"/>he was obliged by my civility, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured <hi>Fontain</hi> that he and all that was in his Houſe, was at my ſervice; and he gave him two of the Books which I deſired, telling him they were the only two that remained; and that as to their printing, <hi>Desbroſſes</hi> who was here Secretary in the year ....... there being then no Reſident, was deſired by Mr <hi>Panajotti</hi> to cauſe print in <hi>Holland</hi> a form of Catechiſm, which he gave him in a Manuſcript, declaring that he would make the expences; that this Secretary having informed the States they cauſed print it on their Charges; that it coſt them four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds to fill the Boxes, in which were many Copies.</p>
                     <p>M. the Reſident added, That being at that time named to come and reſide for the States at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> he was appointed by them to take the charge of theſe Boxes, and to make a Preſent of them to M. <hi>Panajotti:</hi> And that there were a dozen and half of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:137243:45"/>Copies Bound after the <hi>Holland</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, whereof he preſented him twelve; and as to the other ſix, there were no more undiſpoſed of, ſave onely theſe two which he had given me.</p>
                     <p>Finally, That which ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Conviction of the moſt incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous, if any could be, after what is ſaid, is what is ſet down concerning the ſame Book of the Orthodox Confeſſion, in the ſaid Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> Book 8. Chap. 15.</p>
                     <p>In the mean time that theſe Acts and Atteſtations of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church were at the Preſs, the Secretary of the Ambaſſadour arrived at <hi>Paris</hi> from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to bring to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty the Ratification of the Treaty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the Port, and brought with him the Originals of ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Atteſtations, which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs of the Eaſt had entreated the Ambaſſador to cauſe preſent to the King, for juſtification of their Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Calumnies of the <hi>Calvinist</hi>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:137243:46"/>Miniſters. There was amongſt theſe Atteſtations a Manuſcript very ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly Bound, which Mr. <hi>Pana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jotti</hi> made a Preſent of to his Majeſty to be conſerved in his Library, and to ſerve for ever as a Teſtimony of the Faith of the Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ental Church.</p>
                     <p>This Manuſcript is one of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals of the Orthodox Confeſſion; it's Subſcribed by the Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> by many Biſhops, and by ſeveral Officers of the Church of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople:</hi> But whereas the Printed Copies are onely in Greek, this Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript is in Greek and Latin, the Latin being no leſs Original than the Greek.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>There is prefixed to it a new Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> bearing that M. <hi>Panajotti</hi> has cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et out a new Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, at the requeſt of the Patriarch, and that this Gentleman has diſtributed <hi>gratis</hi> Copies throughout the whole Eaſt. Here follows that Atteſtation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:137243:46"/>
                  <head>Dionyſius <hi>by the mercy of God Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>the</hi> New Rome, <hi>and Oecumenical Patriarch.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <q>
                           <p>THoſe who make the holy Books their daily ſtudy, and applies themſelves continually to them, do certainly reap thence very great fruit for Salvation, for it is as a way in which they cannot go aſtray, which leads in a ſupernaural manner, thoſe who aim ſtreight at eternal Glory, and which procures them a happy end; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the Scripture, that he is bleſſed who meditates day and night in the Law of the Lord.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore conſidering that the reading of this Orrhodox Doctrine may be very profitable, which hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been Compoſed ſome years ago by the Orthodox Doctors, approved, received, and confirmed, by the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Patriarchs our Predeceſſors,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:137243:47"/>and printed ſome time after by the care, pains, and expences, of the moſt Wiſe and Orthodox Signior <hi>Panajotti,</hi> firſt Interpreter of the Emperours of the Eaſt and Weſt, our Deareſt Spiritual Son full of Piety and Divine Zeal, with an extraordinary prudence, has <hi>gratis</hi> diſtributed Copies thereof round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to Chriſtians for the publick good. And all the Copies that were Prinred, being employed in this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution which was made of them; ſeveral perſons who earneſtly demands ſo profitable a piece, cannot have it we Judged it our duty to provide for this, and to ſollicite the ſame Signior by his accuſtomed bounry, to ſupply this want, and put remedy to it by a ſecond Edition; holding out to him that he would thereby aquite to himſelf Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation not only equal to that he has already throughout the World, and whereof no perſon is ignorant, but a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and far ſurpaſſing it; to wit, that by which noble Actions becomes immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:137243:47"/>And as he has a fervent zeal and paſſionate deſire of the publick good, ſo he has not neglected our Counſel; but on the contrary, has incontinently by Gods help putten it in execution, and by a ſecond Impreſſion, has given of new a great number of Books to the Faithful; by ſo doing, rendering a piece of important ſervice to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of them, in not ſuffering his Work to be buried in obſcurity: for M. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius Syrigus,</hi> Doctor of the Great Church, has by order of the Patriarch and Synod, laboured moſt carefully to review and ſet the Book in order. Therefore ye Orthodox Chriſtians, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving favourably this Book of the Orthodox Doctrine, as pious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to Souls, give thanks for it to the common Benefactor, and keep it well without ever neglecting the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, for Life eternal is found in the Meditation of the holy Scriptures; which I wiſh all of us may attain to in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord, to whom be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:137243:48"/>Glory for ever. <hi>So be it.</hi> The year 1672. in the Month of <hi>July.</hi> Indicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 5.</p>
                        </q>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Seal of the Patriarch,</hi> Dionyſius <hi>of</hi> Conſtantinople.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>But this Original being in Greek and Latin, I though that if it was needleſs to ſet down the Greek Text, which being a ſtrange Language, would be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by few, it would be fit to inſert here in the Latin Tongue, what is there ſaid of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and which has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been cited in French in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Anſwer.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="question">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:137243:48"/>
                  <head>QUESTIO 106. <hi>Quodnam ſit tertium Myſterium?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EEt Euchariſta, ſive Corpus &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti Domini ſub ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus panis &amp; vini, &amp; realis preſentia. Hoc Sacramentum excillit all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis conducit ſaluti animae nostrae: in hoc enim Sacramento omnis gratiae bonis Chriſti fidelibus manifeſtatur &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="question">
                  <head>In the following Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ANimadvertendum eſt ut Sacerdos habeat talem intentionem, quod ipſa vera ſubſtantia panis &amp; ſubſtantia vini</hi> Tranſubſtantientur, <hi>in verum Corpus &amp; Sanguinam Chriſti, per ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem Spiritus Sancti cujus invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem facit tum temporis ut perficiat Mysterium hoc orando &amp; dicendo Mitte Spiritum Sanctum in nos, &amp; in haec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſita
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:137243:49"/>dona, &amp; fac hunc panem pretio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Corpus Christi tui; quod autem est in hac calice, pretioſum Sanguinem Christi tui, tranſmutans per Spiritum Sanctum. Statim enim ad haec verba fit</hi> Tranſubſtantiatio, <hi>&amp;</hi> Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiantur <hi>panis in verum Corpus Chriſti, &amp; vinum in verum Sanguinem Christi, remanentibus ſolum ſpeciebus viſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; hoc fit ſecundum divinam diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitionem propter duo. Primo ne vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus Corpus Christi, ſed credamus il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud eſſe propter verba prolata à Chriſto Domino,</hi> Hoc eſt Corpus meum, &amp; hic eſt Sanguis meus, <hi>pluſquam ſenſibus noſtris. Siquidem pro hoc promiſit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis beatudinem dicens; Beati qui non vident, &amp; credunt. Secundo quia natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra humana abhorret uſum vivae carnis; &amp; quoniam debet homo uniri Christo Domino per communicationem carnis Christi Domini, &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti Domini; ne igitur abhorreret consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit Dominus dare carnem ſuam, &amp; Sanguinem ſuum in eſum, &amp; potum ſub
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:137243:49"/>ſpecibus panis &amp; vini. De quo diui Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcenus &amp; Gregorius Nyſſenus fuſius diſputant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>De Exibendo Honore qui debetur kuic Myſterio tanquam ipſi Chriſto.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quemadmodem ſanctus Petrus de de ore omnium Apostolorum dixit: Tu es Chriſtus, Filius Dei viventis, ita &amp; nos dicimus cultu Latriae, Credo, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, &amp; confiteor quod tu'es Chriſtus, Filius Dei vivi. Est etiam id My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium Sacrificium pro vivis, &amp; defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis iis qui in ſpe reſurrectionis mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui ſunt; quod Sacrificium ad extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum judicium non ceſſabit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is at the end of the Manuſcript an Act of Legalization of the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, who gives Teſtimony of the Truth of what I have related, whereof the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor follows.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="statement">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:137243:50"/>
                        <p>WE CHARLES R FRANCIS OLIER of <hi>Nointel,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor of the King in his Councils in his Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and Ambaſſador for his moſt Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port, do certifie and atteſt, That the preſent Latin and Greek Manuſcript, entituled, <hi>The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Confeſſion of the Church of the East,</hi> was conſigned into our hands by the Signior <hi>Panajotti,</hi> firſt Interpreter of the Port; who having aſſured us that it would ſerve efficaciouſly to eſtabliſh the verity of the Book bearing the ſame Title, printed by his care, ſeeing it is one of the Originals of it, and has the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Signatures of the Patriarchs at it: He did out of Zeal to vindicate his Church from the Affronts put upon it, entreat us to deal with his Majeſty, that he would be ſo good as to accept of it for the Confuſion of thoſe that would call it in queſtion. And as he lookt upon it as a matter of Conſcience and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:137243:50"/>Honour in imitation of the Patriarchs &amp; Prelates of his Church, to put the matter of fact conteſted, in the greateſt evidence poſſible; he ſent us the laſt year an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the ſame Book by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Patriarch, then holding the See of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which we ſet before that Manuſcript. All theſe Verities being certain, to the end none may doubt of them, we make no difficulty to confirm them by our Subſcription, and the Seal of our Arms, and the Counter-Seal of our firſt Secretary.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Given at our Palace on the Channel of the</hi> Black Sea, <date>
                                 <hi>the Eleventh of September,</hi> 1673.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Olier de Nointel, <hi>Ambaſſadour to his Majeſty at the</hi> Ottoman Port. By my ſaid Lord his Command. <hi>Le</hi> PICARD.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:137243:51"/>
                  <p> What can one ſay againſt this proof? Is not this piece as deciſive as if it had been made in the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> or at <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain?</hi> Is it not beyond all ſuſpicion of having been extorted by the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks? Can any imagine that it could have been altered in the printing, coming onely from the hands of a Greek, a Perſon of Quality moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for his Religion, to thoſe of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, who ſent it to <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> where it was printed at the Charges of the States? Can any thing be imagined more Authentick in the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, ſeeing we find that having been at the very firſt approved by the four Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, and ſeveral Biſhops, it has ſtill continued to be in ſo great eſteem, that the new Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople</hi> deſired to have it reprinted, that it might be the more eaſily ſpread over all and every where.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:137243:51"/>
                  <p> There remains then no more but to prove the ſecond part of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to the end it may be ſaid that we have invincibly ſhewn the Faith of Catholicks concerning the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> to be the ancient Faith of the Church.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:137243:52"/>
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proof of the ſecond part of the Minor, which is, that it is impoſſible there ſhould be made an inſenſible change in the Bel ef of the</hi> Euchariſt <hi>in all the Eaſtern Churches, during the time that has interveened betwixt</hi> Berengarius <hi>and us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere would be no need to be at the pains to prove this, if Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> and the Miniſters who have putten in his hands the Defence of their Cauſe, were not altogether unreaſonable; for having proved moſt clearly in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Section, that theſe Churches were found united in the Belief of the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> in <hi>Berengarius</hi> his time; and in the preceeding Section, that they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently united in the ſame Faith: to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that it was by an inſenſible inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation happened in that interval, they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:137243:52"/>come to the condition they are in at this day, it muſt be feigned that the Eaſtern Churches having embraced the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> in the Eleventh Age, they ſhould reſume ſome time after, that of the <hi>Real Abſence;</hi> and then again by an inſenſible change they ſhould have fallen back again into the ſame condition wherein they certainly were in the Eleventh Age, in believing as they do certainly at this day, the <hi>Real Preſence, Tranſubstantiation,</hi> and the <hi>Adoration</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi> It's ealſiy percieved how ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous this fiction would be.</p>
               <p>But becauſe Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> would not acknowledge this argreement of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churchs with the <hi>Roman</hi> in <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius</hi> his time, for no other reaſon but becauſe it pleaſes him to pretend all is falſe which ſeems diſadvantageous to his Cauſe; we have thought fit to follow him in his wandrings, and to let him ſee, that ſetting aſide all what proves that agreement in <hi>Berengarius</hi> his time, there
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:137243:53"/>is nothing more contrary to common ſenſe, than that which he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade as moſt poſſible, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Greeks</hi> having believed, as he ſuppoſes the <hi>Real Abſence,</hi> until the end of the Eleventh Age, did ſince that time by an inſenſible Innovation, whereof no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory remains come to believe the quite contrary, that is, the <hi>Real Preſence, Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and <hi>Adoration,</hi> which is the ſtate they are found in at this day.</p>
               <p>And it muſt be carefully obſerved, that what we have demonſtratively pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, reaches not only to ſhew that ſome particular perſons of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, or even ſome or ſeveral of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches entirely believes what I ſay; but that it is the manifeſt Belief of the whole Body of theſe Churches; as it is that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church. This then ought to have been the effect of that pretended inſenſible Innovation, in whatſoever time it is placed during the ſix Centuries of years that have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervened
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:137243:53"/>betwixt <hi>Berengarius</hi> and us. And this is what we have ſhewn in the third Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> Book 8. Chap. 21. to be the moſt incredible of all <hi>Chimaeras;</hi> ſo I need no more to prove the ſecond part of the Minor, but to ſet down here what is written there.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The leaſt ſpark of common ſence perceives inſtantly, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the <hi>Latins</hi> being mixed throughout the whole Eaſt ſince the Eleventh Age, with thoſe Societies ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrongly perſwaded of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> having it moſt preſent in their minds more than any other Article, puniſhing in the Weſt with all ſorts of rigour thoſe who doubted of it, and examining carefully all the points of Belief of theſe Societies, which did not agree with their own; that theſe <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins,</hi> I ſay, ſhould not have perceived, during the whole ſpace of ſix hundred years, that theſe Societies had another Faith than they concerning this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:137243:54"/>or that perceiving they ſhould have thought fit to diſſemble it; and that in like manner thoſe Oriental Societies could continue ſix hundred years, either without perceiving in the <hi>Latins</hi> that difference of Belief in ſo important an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rticle, or without up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding it to them, in ſo many Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings they made againſt them.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe two parts, which are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ridiculous, Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ſecond, in his third Anſwer, by maintaining that this came to paſs by the policy of the <hi>Latins</hi> upon one hand, and by the timerouſneſs of the Oriental People on the other; and this we have refuted in the General An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by repreſenting only the abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of this ſuppoſition, according as we ſhall ſet it down here.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> ſuppoſes in the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and in all the other Societies of the Eaſt, that is, in an infinite number of Men, a timerouſneſs of ſix hundred years, hindring them all to riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:137243:54"/>the <hi>Latins,</hi> and to treat them as Idolaters on the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi> He ſtops the <hi>Latins</hi> mouth on the ſame point, by a piece of policy of ſix hundred years continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Neither Charity, nor Zeal, nor the natural inclination Men has to tell the Verity, nor Hatred, nor Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, never makes any of the <hi>Latins</hi> nor any of the <hi>Greeks</hi> belye them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The <hi>Latins</hi> are feared to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Greeks</hi> by this reproach, even then when they are putting them to death; and the <hi>Greeks</hi> are feared to offend the <hi>Latins</hi> on this point, even when they are dying for their Religion, or being in ſecurity, they abandoned themſelves to the greateſt violence of their hatred.</p>
               </q>
               <p>And what is yet more wonderful, is, that the means by which the <hi>Latins</hi> are combined in this politick reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are ſo hidden, that they could never yet be diſcovered in the leaſt; ſo far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that they are practiſed by the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:137243:55"/>Popes, by the Cardinals, by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, by the Prieſts, by the Monks; by the Souldiers, and by the curious Travellers; and ſo efficacious, that they never ſuffered any one perſon to bewray the ſecret. They ſuffer all the other paſſions to act againſt the <hi>Greeks,</hi> they ſuffer the utmoſt rigours to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed againſt them all kind of reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be made to them, even ſuch as naturally ſeems by the thread of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe to lead to the accuſing them of not believing the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> if it could have been made with truth; but it ſtops their Pen and Tongue preciſely when it comes to the point of paſſing to that; and this for the ſpace of ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, not in one onely place, one onely Town, one onely Province, but in the greateſt part of the World.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Here is what Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> endeavours to perſwade thoſe of his Religion, and which he pretends to have rendred probable. Without this twofold ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of a timetouſneſs of ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:137243:55"/>years, domineering in all the Chriſtians of the Eaſt, and ſmothering all other paſſions: and that of another Policy equally laſting amongſt the <hi>Latins,</hi> practiſed by them with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable fidelity, and ſuppreſſing alſo in them all the feelings and inclinations of Nature; Himſelf muſt avow that the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and other Oriental Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, believe the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi> This is what all his Anſwers are reduced to. It is this rare invention which is the ground of the extraordinary ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he declares he has of his Work. It's by this he pretends to have overthrown the Argument of the <hi>Perpetu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty.</hi> But if he be a Man to feed himſelf with his own dreams, I hope there are few who will be of his humour in that, and who will not allow me to conclude againſt him,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That the union of theſe matters of fact we have ſet down, proves with an entire certitude, that the <hi>Greeks</hi> and other Oriental Societies to whom
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:137243:56"/>they may be applied, believes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> as the union of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſame matters of fact proves, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Calviniſts</hi> believes the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That this conſequence extend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> farther, and ſhews not onely that the <hi>Greeks</hi> and other Chriſtians of the Eaſt, are preſently perſwaded of that Doctrine; but that they have been always perſwaded of it ſince <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius;</hi> and conſequently that includes entirely the matter of fact which is found in the firſt Volume of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity;</hi> and that it deſtroys in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular the whole ſecond Book of Mr. <hi>Clauds</hi> Anſwer, to which he had given for Title. <hi>Nullity of the Conſequence:</hi> And which is moſt eaſie and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant to make appear.</p>
                  <p>He ſtrains himſelf in that Book to prove that the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation,</hi> could have been introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced amongſt the <hi>Greeks</hi> and other ſchiſmatical Societies, by the mixture
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:137243:56"/>of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church with them, by the Miſſioners whom the Popes ſent thither, and by the power which the <hi>Latins</hi> had over the Chriſtians of the Eaſt. But granting to Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> all the matter of fact he alledges, there needs no more but to tell him in one word, That they prove exactly the quite contrary of what he pretends, and that it cannot be better proved than by theſe very ſame matters of fact.</p>
                  <p>That which always deludes him, is, that whereas humane Things are tied to innumerable circumſtances, which moſt frequently renders them poſſible or impoſſible, eaſie or difficult, he disjoyns them from all the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to which they are tied, to make metaphyſical Queſtions of them, which he conſiders in a ſpeculative and abſtract manner, as if the matter in hand were of a World ſeparated from ours, whereof we knew no news.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:137243:57"/>
                  <p> He examines in the Air that queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Whether it was poſſible that <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation</hi> (under which he will have the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, though he dare not ſay it) ſhould be introduced ſince <hi>Berengarius,</hi> in the Societies of the Eaſt. And he thinks it enough to find ſome vagrant cauſes, which has a remote and meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſical proportion with that effect. Hence it is that he tells us ſtories which are as uſeleſs for him, as they are uſeful being turned againſt him. But to undeceive him, there needs no more but to oblige him to conſider them ſuch as they are, and to cloath them with all the circumſtances which are really annexed to them.</p>
                  <p>Firſt therefore it is certain that the <hi>Latins</hi> have not totally reduced theſe Societies to an union with the <hi>Latin</hi> Church: if they converted ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, they converted not the whole Body of them: they were not able to make them quit their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:137243:57"/>Opinions, nor change their ancient Diſcipline, to which for the moſt part they adhere as cloſely as ever.</p>
                  <p>Let Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> then include in the firſt place this circumſtance in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion he treats, and let him examine not whether it be poſſible in general that the <hi>Latin</hi> Miſſioners perſwaded all theſe People of the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi> But whether it be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible that theſe Miſſioners, not having been able to make be received in any of theſe Societies, neither the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, nor the points of Diſcipline in which they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreed from her, nor to pacifie their minds toward that Church, nor hinder them to treat her as heretical; yet they generally ſucceeded in making be received in all theſe Societies, a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo ſtrange, as that of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> muſt have ſeemed to thoſe who had been Educated in another Belief.</p>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:137243:58"/>
                  <p> He muſt beſides add to this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, his double Suppoſition of a general timerouſneſs amongſt all the Oriental Chriſtians, and a general po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy amongſt the <hi>Latins,</hi> during all the time he appoints for this change; for as in the progreſs of this introduction, it cannot be ſhewn that the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and other Oriental People unconver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, did withſtand the <hi>Latins</hi> in this point, or took thence ground to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid thoſe who had not yet embraced their Faith; Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> is bound to ſhew us that this introduction is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with theſe two circumſtances; that is to ſay, he ought to make appear it is poſſible that all the unconverted Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern People ſeeing a new Doctrine ſpread amongſt them, did for fear of the <hi>Latins,</hi> ſuppreſs all what natural Jealouſie and the Principles of their Religion could furniſh them of Reaſons and Arguments againſt ſo ſtrange a Doctrine, and that all of them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:137243:58"/>it without any reſiſtance to be introduced in the whole World.</p>
                  <p>He muſt alſo ſhew it poſſible, that all theſe Miſſioners, who converſed amongſt theſe People, and who knew them to be infected with the Errour of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> who all lookt upon this Errour as a damnable Hereſie, who inſtructed them carefully on this point, who ſaw their Doctrine received by ſome and rejected by others, could all without any apparent reaſon, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſilence on this point ſo Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; that none of them accuſed theſe Nations of the Errour of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> none inſerted it into the Catalogue of their Hereſies; none gave notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Popes; none of them made any Books for their Converſion; none uſed any rigour againſt thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to believe the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> how great power ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he had to uſe it: That none in any Book made oſtentation of the ſucceſs of his preaching on this point; none
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:137243:59"/>is found to admire that aſtoniſhing ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſo extraordinary a docility to receive this Doctrine, with ſo inflexible opiniatorneſs to reject all other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine inculcated to them; and that finally they all conſpired to deprive us of the knowledge of ſo great an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
                  <p>This is what Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> ſhould have undertaken to perſwade poſſible, if he would have deſtroyed that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which he impugns in the Title of that ſecond Book, and which he eſtabliſhes by the whole Book it ſelf. But as he durſt not ſo much as attempt it, there needs no more to renverſe all that Book, but to ſhew him what he had to prove, and to make be obſerved that the mixture of the Miſſioners and the power of the <hi>Latins</hi> over the <hi>Greeks</hi> and other Oriental Chriſtians proves very ill that they could make them receive the Doctrine of the <hi>Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Preſence</hi> with theſe circumſtances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but proves perfectly that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:137243:59"/>on one hand they ſhould not have diſcovered that Errour in the <hi>Greeks</hi> and other Eaſtern Chriſtians, if it had been amongſt them; and yet leſs poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible on the other hand, that they ſhould not have upbraided it to them, and endeavoured to root it out, if they had diſcovered it. Whence it follows, that never having done it, by Mr. <hi>Claud</hi>'s own confeſſion they muſt have been altogether free of it. It's the only rational concluſion can be drawn from the matter of fact alledged by Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> in his ſecond Book, and it were to loſe time to refute it after another manner. There needs no proof to eſtabliſh a matter which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perceives with ſo great evidence.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:137243:60"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Some Conſequences which may yet b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> drawn from this Argument, and which neceſſarily follows from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of all Chriſtian Societies in the belief of the</hi> Real Preſence <hi>and</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> proved in this Book.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AS the Scope of this Book was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to illuſtrate more the Proo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Perpetuity of the Faith of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church concerning the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> think it fit to ſet down here ſome Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences which ſprings from it, and ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> clearing which may be drawn from it, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> overturn the Arguments of the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> and to fortifie the Proof of the <hi>Catholicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe Conſequences i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much the more conſiderable, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ruines inſtantly the chief Objections o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:137243:60"/>Proteſtants, and cuts off innumerable important Conteſtations, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the Underſtanding, makes it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe the ſight of Truth.</p>
               <p>Theſe who are acquaint with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how the Proteſtants impugns the Doctrine of the Church, concerning this Myſtery, knows their ſtrongeſt endeavours are employed to turn to their own ſence, the Words by which <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did inſtitute it; and to this they ſtrive to reduce the Queſtion. They make long Treaties, compoſed of many <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> Arguments, to find their own Opinion in theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> they employ long Diſcourſes to explain every Term: The Word <hi>This,</hi> the Word <hi>Is,</hi> the Word <hi>Body,</hi> and all that aims to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that theſe Terms are not to be taken in a proper and literal ſence, but ought to be underſtood in a Figurative and Metaphorical ſence, by ſuppoſing that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> intended only to
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:137243:61"/>teach us by them that he made the <hi>Bread</hi> the Figure of his <hi>Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As there is nothing leſs certain than theſe Arguments, which have no other but obſcure Principles, ſo they agreed not among themſelves, but only in the deſign of impugning the Doctrine of the Church: And when the Queſtion was to explain the meaning of theſe Words, they fell into the confuſion of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable different Explications, which <hi>Luther</hi> reduces to ſeven, and compares to the ſeven Heads of the Beaſt in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">* Habet ſacramentaria ſecta jam, ni fallor, ſex ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pita uno anno nata: mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſpiritus qui ſic diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſibi. Carolſtadii <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> fuit una. quae cecidit. Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glii eſt altera quae cadit oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colampa dii figuratum &amp; Sileſia quae cadit. Cecedit &amp; quarta Carolſtadii qui ſic verba diſpoſuit, quod pro vobis traditur eſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus meum. Quinta ſurgit jam &amp; ſtat in Sileſia.— Hi omnes ſpiritus invicem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi, argutis dimicant diverſis, omnes jactant revelatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes precibus &amp; lacrimis impetratas. <hi>Luth. Ep. ad Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinum claſis 2. locor, comm. cap.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 48.</note> ſome have placed the Figure in the Word <hi>Is,</hi> others in the word <hi>Body;</hi> ſome have put one kind of Figure in them, ſome another kind; and by the different Shuffling together of the Explications,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:137243:61"/>they have given to every one of the Terms, they have produced an extream great variety of different meanings. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolſtadius</hi> will have the word <hi>This,</hi> to relate to the Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which ſate at the Table: <hi>Zuinglius</hi> rejects this Explication, and will have <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> to have given no more but a ſimple Figure of his Body. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> rejects <hi>Zuinglius</hi> his ſence, no leſs than <hi>Luther</hi>'s, and maintains they are both in the wrong, <hi>(Treatiſe of the Supper at the end.) Socinus</hi> rejects <hi>Calvin</hi>'s ſence, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects them all.</p>
               <p>Theſe differences and variety of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are inevitable, as often as men will regulate by Philoſophical Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Arguments, theſe matters whereof they ſhould judge by ſimple impreſſion, and good ſence. One is dazled, and loſes himſelf in theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſical Cogitations, and ceaſes to underſtand what he underſtood before: and that which breeds no difficulty to
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:137243:62"/>thoſe who play not the Philoſopher, and follows ſimply Nature and common Sence, in the ſignification of the Terms, becomes obſcure and inexplicable when it's made the object of theſe kind of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations. Many Examples of this might be given, but for brevities ſake they are omitted.</p>
               <p>Certain it is, when <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced theſe Words, <hi>This is my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> he ſpake not to be underſtood on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Philoſophers and Metaphyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: one the contrary, they are the laſt to whom he would allow the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of theſe Divine Vereties, becauſe their ways are moſt oppoſite to the ways of Faith. He deſigned that his Religion ſhould be followed by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of ſimple People, and thoſe who reaſons little, and dives not to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of things. Who then can doubt but that we ought to judge of the ſence of theſe fundamental Words, ordained to inſtruct us in the belief of this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, by that general and common Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:137243:62"/>which theſe kind of People re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, without ſo many reflections: And conſequently that theſe common Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are the rule of the meaning of theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> ſeeing otherwiſe it would follow that <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> ſhould have led into errour all thoſe who following Nature and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sence, ſhould have <hi>bonâ fide</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood theſe Words in the ſence they imprint naturally.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion then is only to find the ſimple and natural Impreſſion which the Church has received by theſe words. Now what more proper means could be made choice of to perceive the ſence theſe words are taken in without Philoſophy, and without Metaphyſick, in following ſimply Nature and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sence, than to conſult in what ſence they were <hi>de facto,</hi> taken ſince the Apoſtles to this day, by all the Chriſtians of the World, who were not concerned with our Diſputes? And this is ſeen by the agreement of all
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:137243:63"/>Chriſtian Societies in the belief of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> which we have ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolidly proved in this Book; for it's manifeſt they entered not in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, but in taking the Words of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> in a literal ſence; and in underſtanding that after the Conſecration, the Bread became the true Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They did not amuſe themſelves to play the Philoſopher on the meaning of the word <hi>This,</hi> on the meaning of the word <hi>Is,</hi> on the meaning of the word <hi>Body;</hi> they did not ſtudy the tropes and figures, but without ſo many boutways, and reflections, they all conceived that it was the very Body it ſelf of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This is what theſe words bred in their minds; this is what they expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by their Profeſſions of Faith.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> and ſeveral other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, would indeed perſwade us, if they could, that there is nothing more natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and eaſie to find than their figurative ſence they give to theſe Words. For
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:137243:63"/>when there is no more to be done but to aſſert things boldly, and to make ſhew of much confidence, theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men never find themſelves ſtraitned. But to ſee how little ſincere they are in this matter, there needs no more but to read what we have anſwered to them in the two firſt Books of the ſecond Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity.</hi> Certainly if that figurative ſence was ſo eaſie to be found, how came it to paſs that all theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who compoſe thoſe great Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> and who for ſo long a time, have believed the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> did not perceive it? How came it to paſs that <hi>Luther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">* <hi>Epiſtola de argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenſes tome</hi> 7. <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb. fol.</hi> 502. Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vibus curis auxius in haec excutienda ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria multum deſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabam, omnibus nervis extenſis, me extricare conatus ſum, cum probe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciebam hac re Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patui me valde incommodare poſſe... verum me cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum video nulla via elabendi relicta; textus enim Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii nimium apertus eſt &amp; potens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> who ſought after it ſo long time, as a mean which he thought would be ſo advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for him to vex the <hi>Pope,</hi> as he ſays him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, could never find
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:137243:64"/>it? And that after he had bent all his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to that purpoſe, <hi>totis nervis extenſis,</hi> he avows that the Text of the Goſpel is ſo clear, and ſo ſtrong for the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> that it was impoſſible for him to get himſelf rid of it. How did this figurative ſence. I ſay ſo eaſie to be found, not ſhew it ſelf to this man, who is reputed among them as <hi>Calvin (Liv. du. lib. arb. pag.</hi> 311. <hi>in Opuſ.)</hi> aſſures us <hi>for an excellent Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who has erected their Church of new?</p>
               <p>Finally, how does <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> who is alſo one of their Holy Fathers, declare that ſeveral years after he had rejected the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> he knew not yet how to explain theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> by theſe words. <hi>This ſignifies my Body;</hi> and that he learned this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Explication, which he calls <hi>a happy Pearl, foelicem Margaritam;</hi> only from the Letter of a <hi>Hollander,</hi> which he found in the Cloakbag of two
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:137243:64"/>of his Friends, who came to conſult him:
<note place="margin">* Epiſtolam iſtam cujuſdam, &amp; docti &amp; pii Batavi, ſoluta ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina communicarum. In ea foelicem hanc margaritam, <hi>eſt</hi> pro <hi>ſignificat,</hi> hic accipi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veni. <hi>Zuing. Ep. ad Pomeranum, Tom.</hi> 8. <hi>f.</hi> 256.</note> and that it was only by an advertiſement he had in a Dream, from a Spirit, which he ſays he knew not whether it was white or black <hi>(In ſubſidio Euchar. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>f.</hi> 249.) that he learned a paſſage of <hi>Exodus,</hi> which he thought moſt proper to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his <hi>Key of Figure,</hi> as himſelf calle it, if this ſence was ſo natural, and ſo eaſie to find?</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> propoſes in his third An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Pag.</hi> 26. as a means which he pretends is infallible to aſſure him that beliefs concerning a Myſtery, ſuch as is the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> are not formaly in certain Paſſages, where they are ſaid to be, to wit, ſays he, when the eyes do not perceive them, and that they are not in them, in equivalent Terms, or are not drawn from them by neceſſary and evident conſequents, when common
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:137243:65"/>ſence does not diſcern them therein. And he adds, that this proof, although ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, is of the higheſt degree of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and greateſt certainty. But not to ſtay here to ſhew the horrour as a Chriſtian ſhould have at this impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reaſoning, which juſtifies all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; for they need ſay no more than Mr <hi>Claud</hi> does: <hi>If the Truths he would have us believe were in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in formal Terms, our eyes would perceive them; and if they were there in equivalent Terms, or might be drawn thence by evident and neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, our common ſence would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them,</hi> &amp;c. For although they do ill in rejecting a Truth, yet it's true that they do not perceive it: Not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, I ſay, on this, I need no more but to make uſe of this Argument againſt him, and tell him, that if the Belief, and figurative Sence of the Proteſtants were in formal Terms, in the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, our eyes would perceive them; if they were there in equivalent Terms,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:137243:65"/>or might be thence drawn by evident and neceſſary Conſequences; our common ſence would diſcern them; but after having made an exact ſearch by all manner of ways, our eyes and our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence declares they are not there in any of theſe ways; therefore they are not there at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What can Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> deny in this Argument? Not the firſt Propoſition, for it is his own word for word; nor muſt it be the ſecond, for it is undou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btedly true; becauſe certain it is, that neither our Eyes nor our common Senſe diſcovers to us that figurative ſence and belief of Proteſtants, concerning the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> where they ſay it is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: They are not then there accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his principle.</p>
               <p>Perhaps he will ſay that our preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, hinders us to perceive what ſeems to him ſo clear and natural; but beſides, that we will ſay the ſame to him; we will oppoſe to him ſo many millions of Chriſtians of the Eaſt and
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:137243:66"/>Weſt, who for ſo many preceeding Ages, believe the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> and who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perceived that metaphorical and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative ſence. We will oppoſe to him <hi>Luther,</hi> whom <hi>Zuinglius</hi> conſiders as one Eye of the Proteſtant Church, (<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Corpus ſumus, Caput Chriſtus eſt, alter oculus Lutherus eſt,</hi> Zuing. Tom 2. f. 359.) who could not perceive this figurative ſence be ſo much deſired to incommodate the Papacy with, and who was ſo far from being preoccupied againſt this figurative explication, that on the contrary he had a violent incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation leading him towards it, as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf by theſe words, which he adds in his Letter to thoſe of <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg: Prohdolor! plus aequo in hanc partem propenſus ſum.</hi> Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> then muſt avow that his belief concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lords Supper, is not in holy Scripture, ſeeing we do not perceive it there, and ſeeing ſo many millions of Chriſtians never found it there.</p>
               <pb n="217" facs="tcp:137243:66"/>
               <p> I conclude therefore that he is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, with all thoſe who imagines as he does, that there is nothing ſo clear and natural, as his figurative ſence in the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So horrible a miſtake in theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens meaſures ſhould indeed convince them, that all their Arguments muſt be falſe, and all their ways deceitful: And I ſee nothing more unreaſonable than wilfully to continue to follow Guides, who draws them ſo far away from the nature and true rule of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>For ſeeing that the true meaning of the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is doubtleſs that which he intended to ſignifie by theſe words; and that the ſence in which they were to be taken, was not unknown to him; can it be doubted that he had the intention to expreſs the meaning in which theſe words have been actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken by all the Chriſtians of the World, for ſo many Ages by-gone, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than that in which they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:137243:67"/>by a ſmall number of <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> in the Eleventh Age, whoſe Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader did thrice abjure his Doctrine as an Hereſie, and by a few Sects of the late Age, who mutually condemn one another of Errour and Impiety, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Socinians,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> the <hi>Independents,</hi> the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I know well that Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> pretends that the Believers of the firſt eight Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies, which he calls the fair days of the Church, (<hi>Anſwer to the Treatiſe</hi> part 2. chap. 3. p. 295.) during which he ſays, errour durſt not appear, did underſtand the words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the ſence thoſe of his Religion under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands them: But we have now right to ſuppoſe the contrary, as a matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond debate, becauſe we have proved it in ſo convincing a manner in the laſt two Tomes of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> that he has not been able to anſwer to it; and we have ſo ſecured the proofs of Catholicks from the Cavils and Subtilties of the
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:137243:67"/>Miniſters, that it is impoſſible they can obſcure them.</p>
               <p>But though we had not ſhewn, as we have done in theſe Works, that the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers of theſe firſt Ages had no other Belief concerning the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> but that which we have at preſent; it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have ſhewn by unqueſtionable proofs, which are reduced to a compend in this Book, the union and agreement of all Chriſtian Societies for ſo many Ages, in the belief of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> becauſe that union and agreement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides inſtantly the ſence of Tradition, in letting us ſee, that ſeeing this Doctrine could not be eſtabliſhed by Innovation, it muſt be the original Doctrine of the Church, and conſequently that the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers of the firſt Ages, had the ſame belief concerning this Myſtery, as thoſe of the following Ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:137243:68"/>
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Argument of the Perpetuity ſerves alſo to decide the Controverſie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the meaning of the expreſſions of the holy Fathers, in matter of the</hi> Euchariſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Argument which proves the Agreement of all the Eaſtern So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, in the Belief of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> for ſo many Ages, does not only ſhew us Tradition concerning the literal ſence of the words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It alſo decides inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Controverſie we have with the Proteſtants, concerning the meaning of thoſe expreſſions which are found ſo frequent in the Books of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the:
<note place="margin">1. Tertul. contra Marc. c. 4. Euſeb. Caeſar. in Parall. Damaſc. l. 3. c. 45: Cyrill. Hieroſol. 4. Catech. myſt Greg. Nyſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de Bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. Aug Serm: 87. de div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſis citat: à Beda <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Epiſt. ad Corinth. c. 10.2. Gaud. tract. 2. in Exod. 3. Greg. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ. Orat. Catech. Amb. de init. c. 4. Cyrill. Catech. 4. myſt. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. emiſſ. Sſſrm. 5. de Paſch. 4. Juſtin Mart. Apol. 2. Iraen. l. 4. c. 4. Theoph. Antioch. 6. Chryſ. Hom. 83. in Matth. 7. Aug. Ep. ad Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua. 2. Optat.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Bread is made the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. 2. <hi>That of Bread and Wine are made the
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:137243:68"/>Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. 3. <hi>That the Bread and Wine are changed, converted, and tranſelemented into the Body and Blood, and in to the Substance of the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. 4. <hi>That they are the Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>after the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration</hi> 5. <hi>That we are made partakers of the Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. 6. <hi>That we touch and eat the Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>himſelf.</hi> 7. <hi>That the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>enters into the mouth of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</hi> 8. <hi>That his Body and Blood dwells upon our Altars: That it is the proper Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>That we receive truly his precious Body: That it is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This Controverſie conſiſts to know if theſe words, and innumerable others
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:137243:69"/>like them which are found in the Books of theſe holy Doctors, ought to be taken in the proper and literal ſence, as the Catholicks maintain, or if they are to be underſtood in a figurative and metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical ſence, as the Miniſters pretend. Now this Queſtion is decided by the Agreement of all Chriſtian Societies in the Article of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> ſince the Apoſtles, it being they could not believe that Doctrine, unleſs they had taken theſe expreſſions in a proper and literal ſence.</p>
               <p>I know that <hi>Aubertin</hi> ſtrives to elude all theſe paſſages of the Fathers, which the Catholicks make uſe of to prove their Doctrine, by propoſing other paſſages which ſeem like to them, and which both in Scripture and in Fathers are taken in a metaphorical ſence: And I muſt avow, that if in this point he ſhews no great exactneſs of Judgment, at leaſt he lets us ſee he is a man that has read very much; for that collection he makes of Expreſſions, ſeeming like to
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:137243:69"/>thoſe he would explain, could not have been done without a great deal of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: And I may ſay, that in taking from this Miniſter that compariſon of metaphorical Paſſages, with thoſe we make uſe of, we take from him all what has any ſhow, and what might dazle ſimple people. Wherefore it is moſt important to make appear the abuſe he makes of theſe compariſons.</p>
               <p>And for this end there are two ways, the one longer, and the other more ſhort. The firſt is, to ſet down preciſely by Arguments the difference of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which he compares, and to ſhew that they are no ways alike; and that the one ought to have been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in a metaphorical ſence, and the other for ſimple and literal expreſſions: And this is what we have done in the ſecond Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> in a manner ſo convincing, as has made Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> unable to reply; and we have ſhewn there, that all theſe compariſons of expreſſions which <hi>Aubertin</hi> makes,
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:137243:70"/>are all falſe, and diſcovers him to have had no exactneſs of Judgment.</p>
               <p>This way is no doubt very good for thoſe who have leiſure to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to this examination, and who have their Underſtandings framed for theſe ſomewhat-abſtract Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But it is long, becauſe there are a great number of expreſſions and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages to be explained. And it muſt be moreover granted, that it is not the ordinary way men uſes to diſcern Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions by, they diſtinguiſh very well thoſe that are different, they do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe them together, they miſs not to give one meaning to the one, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning to the other, without making expreſs reflections, unleſs very ſeldom on the differences that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them. Yea, there are many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are not capable to make thoſe reflections, and yet never are miſtaken in the ſence of theſe different Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. How then do they diſtinguiſh them? By a ſimple view of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:137243:70"/>by an impreſſion which makes it ſelf be perceived, they know theſe Expreſſions have different meanings, though perhaps they would be much puzled to point out the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them. It's after this manner that men judges almoſt of the diverſity of all things in the World.</p>
               <p>It is then manifeſt that the common way men has to diſtinguiſh Things and Expreſſions, is the diverſity of impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they make upon the mind: So whoever is certain that Words form different impreſſions on the Mind, knows at the ſame time that they are different, whether he can or cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain what diſtinguiſhes them: Men requires no more, and they ſtand not in need of that perplexity of reaſoning.</p>
               <p>Wherefore to renverſe all thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons of Expreſſions, which <hi>Aubertin</hi> has made with ſo much toil and labour, it is enough to anſwer, That Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the more common and ſureſt Rule of the diſtinction of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:137243:71"/>diſtinguiſhes and ſets apart all thoſe he alledges as like; becauſe men by following their impreſſion, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways taken the one in one ſence, and the others in another ſence.</p>
               <p>He ſays theſe words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, This is my Body,</hi> are like to thoſe others of the Scripture, <hi>The ſeven Cows are ſeven years: The Rock was Christ: The King is the Head of Gold.</hi> But we tell him he is miſtaken, and at the ſame time we let him ſee it by a certain and deciſive proof; to wit, that never any perſon believed that the Cows were really ſeven years, nor that the Rock was really <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> nor that the King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had really a Head of Gold: But all the Nations of the World, have upon theſe Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, This is my Body,</hi> believed the conſecrated Bread to be really the Body of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> as we have ſhewn in this little Book, and conſequently thoſe Expreſſions are very far diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
               <pb n="227" facs="tcp:137243:71"/>
               <p> He ſays that expreſſion of St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> That <hi>the Bread is changed into the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, is like to that of St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> That <hi>all what we think, what we ſay, and what we do, is changed by the fire of the Holy Spirit;</hi> or what St. <hi>Cyril</hi> ſays, That <hi>we are changed into the Son of God:</hi> But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſetting down here what is ſaid in the ſecond Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> Book 6. where we have explained theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and others which this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter objects, as like to whoſe which carries, that the Bread is changed into the Body of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> &amp;c. and where we have ſhewn the difference betwixt them: To renverſe this Sophiſm of <hi>Aubertin,</hi> it is ſufficient to ſay they are certainly different, ſeeing the one has never imprinted that idea on any perſon, that thoughts, words, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were really changed into a ſpiritual ſubſtance, or that we are really changed into the Son of God: And that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have perſwaded all the Nations
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:137243:72"/>of the World, that the Bread was real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changed into the very Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lo here the ſureſt Rule for the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Expreſſions, and there needs no more but to apply it to all the falſe compariſons of <hi>Aubertin,</hi> and other Miniſters, either out of the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or holy Fathers: For ſtill we find that the common and univerſal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of all Nations, has ſo diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thoſe Expreſſions which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as like, that they never have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded them together; and that they have always taken the one in one ſence, and the other in another.</p>
               <p>This ſhews that all the ſubtility of the Miniſters, tends onely to obſcure common ſence, and their way of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing terminates in blindneſs, as well as in Hereſie. Let men act according to the common impreſſion, and they will have no difficulty to underſtand that when St. <hi>Chryſologue</hi> ſays, <hi>That Gold changes Men into Beasts;</hi> he does not
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:137243:72"/>mean that it changes them really into Beaſts: &amp; the ſame impreſſion has on the contrary made them judge, that when in the Liturgies, we pray God to ſend his Holy Spirit to change the Bread and the Wine into his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> we underſtand that we pray him to change them really and effectually: they never had the leaſt difficulty concerning the meaning of theſe expreſſions: they diſtinguiſhed them perfectly, and did always take them, the one in a Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Sence, the other in a Sence of Reality.</p>
               <p>What then do the Miniſters pretend, when they compare all theſe Figurative Expreſſions of the Scripture and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with that in which it's ſaid, that it is the Body, the proper Body, the true Body, the very ſelf ſame Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> and endeavours to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that the one and the others muſt be taken in the ſame Figurative Sence. They pretend by the exteriour and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial reſemblance of theſe Terms, to
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:137243:73"/>which they apply their minds, to ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the view and clear ſentiment, by which we diſtinguiſh ſo neatly thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions without any confuſion; that is to ſay, they endeavour to extinguiſh in men, the light of common Sence, and to render them material and ſtupid, by filling their minds with theſe vain ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. This is ſufficient for any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man to reject all that vain Pomp of Compariſons, in which are repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as like theſe expreſſions which men have never confounded together as like. And there needs no more to overturn all what is conſiderable in <hi>Aubertins</hi> Book conſequently the <hi>noble Victory,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> ſayes
<note place="margin">* Anſw. to the 2. Treatiſe ch. 1. p. 50.</note> that Book has obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned over the <hi>Roman</hi> School is no more but a meer illuſion of this Miniſter.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> in his third Anſwer, Book 5. Chap. 10. allows of this manner of diſcerning expreſſions, and even things themſelves, by the impreſſion and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent which they form, no leſs than
<pb n="631" facs="tcp:137243:73"/>by an exact obſervation of the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which diſtinguiſhes them. But he would have us to let him ſee that in the firſt ſix Ages, the expreſſions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were taken in a Sence of reality; and the others which the Miniſters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as like in a Metaphorical Sence; and not to ſeek that difference of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in the following Ages, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that the Doctrine was changed in them. He ought then to be content ſeeing we have ſatisfied his demaund, how unreaſonable ſoever it be, for we have proved to him in the ſecond Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> to which he could not anſwer that difference of expreſſion of the Fathers, as like to thoſe which we produce, and we have confirmed this Proof in the third Tome, and in the general Anſwer, in ſuch a manner, as he is beaten down under it, in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him ſee that all he could ſay to perſwade the change he ſuppoſes in the Doctrine of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> is the moſt manifeſt Proof of his want of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:137243:74"/>To this comes all he has written to maintain as he has done, with an inflexible opiniatorneſs, that fable on which he has employed all his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and his big Words. There needs no more, for his ſilence ſhews ſufficiently that he is convinced.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="233" facs="tcp:137243:74"/>
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The figurative Explication, which the</hi> Calviniſts <hi>give to theſe words,</hi> This is my Body, <hi>renders them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incapable to prove their Belief concerning the</hi> Euchariſt, <hi>to thoſe who deny it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere is no Errour which the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts</hi> have taken more pains to vindicate themſelves of, than that of admitting no more but ſimple Signs, and without efficacy. For as the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion people had, that they taught this Hereſie, confirmed by the reproach made them ordinarily by the <hi>Lutheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and even by ſome <hi>Catholicks,</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them very odious, they uſed all their endeavours to take it away, and ſhew it was a Calumny. All their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, all their Declarations, all their Confeſſions of Faith are full of formal
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:137243:75"/>Condemnations and Anathema<hi>'s</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Errour, that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> conrains no more but ſimple Figures.
<note place="margin">* Apud Hoſpini, hiſt. Sacrament. 2. part. fol. 124, 128, 135, 147.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Afrer theſe expreſs Condemnations, they cannot refuſe to avow that if this Errour they ſo earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, and which they charge upon the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> be a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence of the Figurative Sence they give to the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and if this Sence puts them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an abſolute inability to prove their Belief concerning the Supper; it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows neceſſarly, according to their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that this ſence is falſe; and that their explication is erroneous. Now there is nothing more eaſie to prove than this their inability, to juſtify themſelves of this Errour which they condemn, and to prove their Belief to the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and all who will deny it; for there needs no more but to propoſe, what they teach in their Confeſſion of Faith, in
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:137243:75"/>their Catechiſms, and the Books of thoſe who are Authors of them, and then to require the Proof thereof from the Scripture, which according to them is alone ſufficient to ground their Faith.</p>
               <p>They ſay in their Catechiſm, Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day 51, where they ſpeak of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt repreſents to them by the Bread his Body, and by the Wine his Blood. And in the</hi> 37 <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of their Confeſſion of Faith, That in the Supper, God gives them really and in effect that which he figurates therein.</hi> In their 53 Sonday, <hi>That Jeſus Christ, with whom their Souls are inwardly nowriſhed, is in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> and that they <hi>are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipant of his proper Substance;</hi> or as they ſpeak in their own Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>That they are therein nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and quickned by the Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's according to this Perſwaſion and Belief that <hi>Calvin,</hi> who is the Author of this Catechiſm, ſays, in the 4 Book
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:137243:76"/>of his Inſtitutions, Chap. 17 n. 11. <hi>That in the Supper,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally given us under the Signs of Bread and Wine; yea his Body and his Blood by which he has purchaſed Salvation to us, and thereby we are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipant of his Substance.</hi> And his is conform to what <hi>Beza</hi> ſays in the conference of <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> as he relates him ſelf in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 496. <hi>That the thing ſignified in this Sacrament is offered and given us of the Lord, as truly as the Signs of it, that the Body and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>which are truly communicated to us, are truly preſent in the uſe of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, although they are neither under, nor beſide, nor in the Bread and Wine, nor in any other place but in Heaven.</hi> And in the <hi>pag</hi> 515, that we are made <hi>participant only of the fruit of Chriſts death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the <hi>Calvinists</hi> Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Cene or Supper, and for which we maintain they cannot give
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:137243:76"/>Proofs from the Scripture alone unleſs they renounce the figurative ſence, they give to the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The queſtion is nor here of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner according to which they ſay they receive all theſe things, whether it be by Faith, or otherwiſe; but of what they receive: nor is the queſtion here of Mr. <hi>Clauds</hi> analogical and meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſical Arguments, but of clear and preciſe Proofs from Scripture, ſeeing they are ſolemnly bound to ſhew there all their points of Faith.</p>
               <p>If they alledge theſe words, <hi>Take, eat, this is my Body,</hi> a <hi>Socinian</hi> will anſwer them, that they ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to receive any other thing, than what <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> has commanded to be taken, but according to them, he intended only to ſay <hi>Take, eat, this is the Figure of my Body,</hi> therefore they receive only the Figure, and not the Body.</p>
               <p>If they reply, that theſe Words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Promiſe, and that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="238" facs="tcp:137243:77"/>promiſed to give them his Body in giving them a Figure of it. The <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> will anſwer, he ſees not that Promiſe in the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and he will oppoſe to them what <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius</hi> ſays <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>f.</hi> 371. <hi>That theſe words of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>contain no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs at all, Nihil in his nobis promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt,</hi> and on the margent; <hi>Chriſti verba hoc eſt Corpus meum promiſſionem nullam continent.</hi> And what <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays in his manner of reforming the Church, <hi>pag.</hi> 122. <hi>ſecond of his Opuſc.</hi> that <hi>he who ſeeks in the Sacrament more than the promiſes contain, the Devil has bewitched him:</hi> And he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from the Principles of theſe two Reformers, that one ought to ſeek no more in this Sacrament but a Figure: unleſs he be bewitched by the Devil.</p>
               <p>So that holding to <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> it muſt be ſaid the <hi>Socinians</hi> have reaſon to laugh at the Promiſes the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> think to find in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body:</hi> and in holding to what the
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:137243:77"/>
                  <hi>Calviniſts</hi> ſays of this Promiſe, all the Anathema's they pronounce againſt the <hi>Socinians</hi> fall back on <hi>Zuinglius</hi> himſelf who agrees with them, that there are no Promiſes in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is already no ſmall advantage that the chief of all the Sacramentari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, he who is pretended to have been raiſed up by God, to re-build anew the pretended Reformed Church, is anathematized by thoſe who call them ſelves his Diſciples. But leſt the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy take them to quite <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> to preſerve that promiſe, I maintain more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over that <hi>Zuinglius</hi> reaſons well, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their common Principles, and it is only <hi>Calvin</hi> and his Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors who reaſon ill.</p>
               <p>For by what ſubtility can they diſcover in theſe words, <hi>Take, eat, this is my Body,</hi> taken in a figurative ſence, a Promiſe made by <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> to give truly his Body? <hi>This is a Figure of my Body,</hi> is that to ſay, <hi>take, eat, I
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:137243:78"/>promiſe to give you really my Body?</hi> Is this a reaſonable Concluſion? <hi>This is the Figure of the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, therefore this Figure contains or conferrs really the ſame Body.</p>
               <p>Does not common ſence dictate the contrary, that it is not neceſſary that a Figure contain, or confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the thing ſignified; that they are two things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together diſtinct: and to uſe the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples themſelves, alledges to prove their figurative ſence; when <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſays to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the ſeven Kowes are ſeven Years, did he mean that the Kowes contained the ſeven Years. When God ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> that the Lamb was the Paſſage, he meant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Proteſtants, it was the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Paſſage, but he meant not that the Lamb contained or conferred the Paſſage.</p>
               <p>Theſe Gentlemen, who make ſo great uſe of Logick in all their Books, ſhould they not have acknowledged that the Concluſion depending on two
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:137243:78"/>Premiſſes or Propoſitions, that which is in queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Eucharist</hi> contains or conferrs the Body of <hi>Jeſus</hi> can have no connexion with that other, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is the Figure of the Body of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> but by an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Propoſition; <hi>viz.</hi> all Figures contain or communicate the thing they ſignify; from which it would follow, that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> being the Figure of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>'s Body, it ſhould commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate his Body: but as that Major is extravagant, the connexion the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters would make of their conſequence <hi>that the</hi> Euchariſt <hi>communicats the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>or it is effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, with that Explication, <hi>that it's the Figure of the Body of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, is no leſs impertinent.</p>
               <p>I find not in all the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> Books but one Argument to ſupport this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity; which is, that it is unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God to feed us with an empty Spectacle; and therefore, we muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:137243:79"/>believe, that when he eſtabliſhes a Sign, the verity of the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied is alſo preſent. Whence they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that God having eſtabliſhed the Bread as the Sign of his Body, by theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſame Body muſt be joyned to the Bread, and it muſt be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to us by his Spirit: for, <hi>unleſs one will call God a deceiver</hi> (ſays Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin) <hi>he dare not ſay that a vain Sign, and void of the verity is propoſed by him,</hi> (<hi>Just.</hi> book 4. chap. 17. n. 10.)</p>
               <p>I proteſt hitherto it was not poſſible for me to find the leaſt ſpark of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence in this Argument, and I can not enough admire how People who makes ſo ſolemn profeſſion, to admit nothing but Scripture, or evident and neceſſary conſequences drawn from it, ſhould take the boldneſs to propoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Holy Scriptures, ſuch reaveries and dreams.</p>
               <p>For what ground were there to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe God of deceiving, if commanding
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:137243:79"/>us to take no more but the ſign of his Body, he gave no more at the ſame time but the Figure of his Body? Is it to cheat men, to give them preciſely what is promiſed them? Why is it a vain deluſory thing, and unbeſeeming God to eſtabliſh a Figure of a thing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? Was it a vain and deluſory thing to make the Paſchal Lamb a Figure of the Angels paſſing by the houſes of the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> when he deſtroyed the firſt born of the <hi>Egyptians?</hi> And would it be to argue in any manner ſupportable to ſay according to <hi>Calvin</hi>'s opinion, that ſeeing the Paſchal Lamb was a Figure of that paſſage of the Angel, therefore that paſſage muſt always have been preſent; otherwiſe God had been a deceiver in propoſing falſe ſigns.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> in his Anſwer to Father <hi>Nouet, pag.</hi> 320. compares that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion he attributes to the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they celebrated their Eaſter: <hi>This is the bread of affliction, which our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eated in</hi> Egypt, to theſe words
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:137243:80"/>
                  <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and he ſays, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, in ſubſtituting the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the new Covenant to that of the Old, he would retain the ſame form of expreſſion, and in ſtead of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; this is the bread of affliction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he has ſaid, this is my Body which is broken for you:</hi> ſo that according to this Miniſter, this Bread of affliction are two Memorials, the one of the Old Teſtament, and the other of the New, expreſſed after the ſame figurative manner
<note place="margin">* See the anſwer to this objection of Mr. Claud, in the 2 Tome of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. P. 196.</note> in aſcribing to the Sign the thing ſignified. Now it were ridiculous to conclude and ſay; that the bread the <hi>Jews</hi> eated in cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating their Eaſter, being the Figure and Memorial of the affliction their Fathers endured in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ought to have been accompanied with the thing ſignified, and communicate to them the efficacy thereof, leſt it had been a deceitful ſign. It is no leſs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, will a <hi>Socinian</hi> ſay to Mr. <hi>Claud</hi>
                  <pb n="245" facs="tcp:137243:80"/>to pretend to prove that the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> would be a deceitful ſign, if the Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> were not therein communicate and received.</p>
               <p>The inſtitution of Sacraments is an arbitrary thing, depending wholly on the will of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> he has made them the Inſtruments of his Graces in the New Teſtament, to which he was not obliged; he could, if he had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed have inſtituted among the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, pure ſigns, deſtitute of efficacy, as he had inſtituted among the <hi>Jews;</hi> theſe ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s would neither have been vain, nor falſe, nor deluſory, they would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Effect for which they ſhould have been ordained by God; which is to repreſent to us the things ſignified, and this repreſentation having nothing in it ſelf but what's lawful, though God had not annexed any Grace to it, there had been no ground to ſay that he had deceived men by a vain or empty ſhow. There muſt then be a promiſe of Grace joyned to the eſtabliſhment of a ſign,
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:137243:81"/>to conclude rationally that the thing ſignified is joyned with it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently theſe words <hi>This is my Body,</hi> taken in the meaning of the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> containing no more but the inſtitution of Bread, as a ſign of the Body of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ.</hi> It's a manifeſt abſurdity to aſſert they import a promiſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement on God's part, to give real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Body to thoſe who ſhould take the Signs of it.</p>
               <p>Perhaps the Miniſters will anſwer, true it is, the promiſe of that real re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Body of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> which they believe is not contained in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> but it's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in other Paſſages, as in the 6 <hi>chap.</hi> of St. <hi>John,</hi> and in theſe words of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>The Bread which we break is it not the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This is what muſt be examined in few words.</p>
               <p>As to the 6 of <hi>John,</hi> it is clear they cannot make uſe of it to prove their
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:137243:81"/>belief concerning the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> ſeeing they hold with the <hi>Lutherians,</hi> that the Evangeliſt ſpeaks not of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in all that Chapter, <hi>There is no word of the Supper here,</hi> ſays <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> on the 53 verſ. <hi>but of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al communication of the Fleſh of Christ which we have without the uſe of the Supper.</hi> And he adds, <hi>Theſe of</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia <hi>have not adduced this paſſage pertinently, to prove that all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhould receive the Cup.</hi> They could not then be thought to deal ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, if they ſhould alledge this Chapter to prove their belief concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Supper, ſince they judge the Evangeliſt does not ſpeak of it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>As to the paſſage of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that being taken in the true ſence, which is that of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> it includes that of receiving the Fleſh of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> which is a conſequence of that Preſence: But it cannot ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally be concluded according to the
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:137243:82"/>
                  <hi>Calvinists,</hi> for firſt <hi>Zuinglius</hi> cuts off at one ſtroak all the conſequences they can draw from it, by pretending that the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> does not ſignifie Communion or Participation of the Body of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of People who live upon the Body and Blood of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and that by eating this Bread, one declares himſelf a member of the Church, <hi>Tom.</hi> 2 <hi>fol.</hi> 211.258.342.</p>
               <p>Beſides this explication of <hi>Zuinglius</hi> whoſe Authority ſhould be conſiderable to the Miniſters, becauſe of the rank he holds among thoſe who have erected their Church of new. They them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves furniſh us with others, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the conſequences they can draw from that paſſage: for who can hinder a <hi>Socinian</hi> to explain theſe words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in a figurative ſence, as themſelves explain theſe of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and who can hinder him to ſay that theſe words muſt be ſo rendered. The Bread which we break is it not the ſign
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:137243:82"/>or figure of the Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as they render theſe others, this is the ſign or figure of my Body.</p>
               <p>Now how can they conclude from thence, that in receiving this Figure, they receive really and in effect the thing figured, unleſs it be by a great number of groundleſs ſuppoſitions, and by ſupplying from their own imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what the Scripture ſays not at all. They muſt then, will they, nill they, confeſs that the figurative ſence they give to the words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt This is my Body</hi> is altogether falſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo manifeſtly contrary not only to that which all Chriſtians who believe the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> ſince the Apoſtles have given to them, but alſo to the Principles of the Miniſters. They muſt therefore renounce it to defend their belief concerning the eating and receiving the Body and Blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in their Supper.</p>
               <p>Here is moreover another advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage drawn from the main Argument
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:137243:83"/>and we cannot ſufficiently admire the care the Divine Providence has had to guard this Myſterie of our Faith with ſo great abundance of Proofs, againſt the incredulity of men</p>
               <p>For it muſt be obſerved, that altho' commonly it follows not that he who errs in one Point, errs alſo in another altogether diſtinct from it. Yet God has ſo diſpoſed things, as it follows ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, that if the <hi>Calvinists</hi> err in any one of the Points upon which we accuſe them of Hereſie; their Doctrine concerning the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is falſe, and ours is true. To be convinced of this, there needs only to conſider two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, the one of Right, the other of Fact, both equally certain.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, It's impoſſible the truth of the Myſterie of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> ſhould be known only by a Society of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and that all other Societies ſhould be in errour, concerning ſo capital and important a Point; for if this ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition were poſſible, it would be alſo
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:137243:83"/>poſſible that the whole World might be in errour, and that there were no Orthodox Church at all, ſeeing that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Society, which ſhould know the truth of the Myſterie of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> would be Heretical in all other Points and all the other Societies would be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical in point of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond is, There is none at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the world, but only the Society of the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and thoſe who have ſprung from it, or have riſen up with it, as the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> who deny the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi> This cannot be doubted of after the Proofs we have above ſet down.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, it follows neceſſarily that if the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> had reaſon to deny this <hi>Preſence,</hi> all the other Societies muſt have been in errour as to this Point: and it being impoſſible, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as I have ſaid, that the truth of this Myſterie ſhould be known only by Hereticks, there needs no more but to convince the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> of Hereſig up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:137243:84"/>any other Point that's common to them with the Sacramentarians to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, thence demonſtrativly that they are alſo Heriticks in matter of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> becauſe otherwiſe it would follow, that notwithſtanding of their being Herericks, they alone ſhould know the truth of this Myſterie, which is altogether impoſſible.</p>
               <p>Wherefore they are not conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces only probable, but entirely certain and demonſtrative: To ſay the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> are Hereticks, in condemning as Idolatry, the Invocation of Saints, the Honour that's given to their Reliques, as is invincibly proved in <hi>the Anſwer to the writing of a Miniſter, upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral points of Controverſie.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Doctrine concerning the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist</hi> is falſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Calviniſts</hi> are Heriticks in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting Prayer for the Dead, in promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Salvation to their Children dead with out Baptiſm <hi>&amp;c,</hi> as we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated in the laſt chapter of the
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:137243:84"/>
                  <hi>Defence of the Faith of the Church, for anſwer to a letter of Mr.</hi> Spon. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Doctrine concerning the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> is falſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Calvinists</hi> are Heriticks in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that <hi>the state of the Church was interrupted, in ſo far as it was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry according to them, that God ſhould raiſe up People, in an extraordinary manner, to erect the Church of new,</hi> This we have likewiſe proved, ſo as admits no reply, in the firſt part of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Spon.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their belief concerning the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> is falſe.</p>
               <p>So there needs no more but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of errour upon any Point they have taken for pretext of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the Catholick Church, to conclude that their belief in point of the <hi>Eucharist</hi> is falſe.</p>
               <p>How remote ſoever theſe particular conſequences ſeem to be from theſe Principles, the two general Maxims we have fixed; <hi>That it's impoſſible this
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:137243:85"/>Mysterie ſhould be known only by He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks;</hi> and yet the Sacramentarians only <hi>deny the Real Preſence,</hi> joyns and knitts them together by an indiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble knot.</p>
               <p>Wherefore all the Proofs of other controverted Points, are convictions of the errour of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in point of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi> And this is what ought carefully to be remarked, that it's ſufficient to convince them of errour upon any article of Faith whatſomever, to conclude the ſame of their Doctrine of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this Myſterie ſupports the whole Catholick Religion, ſo the ſame whole Religion ſupports it; all the Proofs, which eſtabliſhes the ſeveral Points, that divides us from the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> meet and joyn in this, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forms ſuch abundance of light and conviction, that it's impoſſible thoſe who ſincerely open the eyes of their Soul to look upon it, to reſtrain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from crying out in a rapture
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:137243:85"/>with the Royal Prophet, <hi>Teſtimonia tu a credibilia facta ſunt nimis.</hi> Pſal. 92.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI. The Concluſion.</head>
               <head type="sub">Where once more the invincible Strength of this Argument is expoſed.</head>
               <p>I Can hardly perſwade my ſelf that the Miniſters, who have ſo high an eſteem of reaſoning, as that they ground their Faith upon it, ſeeing they cannot find it in the Scripture, but by the help of their conſequences, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſo to overthrow the Rules thereof, as that not being able to find any thing of falſhood either in the Major, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of a Regular Argument, will yet hazard to deny the concluſion of it.
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:137243:86"/>And at the ſame time. I can leſs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what they can ſay to obſcure the clearneſs and evidence of what was proved in the Major and the Minor. It ſeems then there is good ground to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that they will be forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that in the Book of the <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> it's moſt ſolidly proved. that the Faith of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, concerning the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> which is the ſame with that of all the <hi>Oriental</hi> Churches, is the ancient and perpetual Faith of the Chriſtians of all Ages, and that conſequently their opinion which is contrary thereto, is a manifeſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy.</p>
               <p>Yet this is a thing we do not hope for, unleſs it be of ſome particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whom God may touch by his Grace: But as to the generality of the Miniſters, we know their Genius better, than to promiſe to our ſelf that they will yeeld to the Truth how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſoever it may be, they are too much infatuate with their ridiculous
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:137243:86"/>Opinion of being come out of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> as to be able to reſolve to return again to it. That which will ſeem moſt convincing to them, will paſs in their conceit for <hi>a ſong of Tyre,</hi> which imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tats the Tune of the ſongs of <hi>Sion,</hi> or for a crafty ſeducing of the Beaſt of the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> whoſe horns are like thoſe of the Lamb. They will rather choiſe to put out their own eyes than to be attentive to it. They will ſay Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> has given ſatisfaction to all that, and it's only an idle repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what has been confuted by their <hi>most Reverend Brother,</hi> and deſerves no anſwer. Or if they make any, it will not be in anſwering directly and preciſely to every Article; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting ſincerely the Proofs which ſupport all what is aſſerted, by referring to the Books whence they are taken, being for brevities ſake, we were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not to ſet them down at length; but they will do nothing but confuſe and ravel the Diſpute by new incidents, to
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:137243:87"/>break the threed of it, and thereby hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſimple People of their Party, from ſeeing ſo eaſily the truth through the clouds, wherewith they will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to cover it.</p>
               <p>But do what the Miniſters will, I can hardly believe that theſe who have Wit, Conſcience, and Honour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Proteſtants will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by this Argument, that what we believe of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and what all thoſe great Societies of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves with us, is the common and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Faith of the whole Church, and conſequently, that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
               <p>For as to the matters of fact, which ſhows the agreement of theſe Churches either in <hi>Beringarius</hi> his time, or at this time, they are too well grounded to be queſtioned in ſincerity; ſo it's not like they can doubt of the truth of the Major, which is proved in Sect. 1. and 5.</p>
               <p>And as to the impoſſibility of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:137243:87"/>Change,</hi> theſe matters of fact being ſuppoſed, it appears ſo eaſily of it ſelf, as it would ſeem we ought not to have ſought Reaſons to make it be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perceived, if Mr. <hi>Claud</hi>'s pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs had not obliged us to it: But yet we needed no more, but to lay open the incredible abſurdities, which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally included in the imagination of this inſencible change, to ſet the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of this Fable, upon the higheſt Point of evidence.</p>
               <p>All I fear, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> is that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence you have from your Infancy, to a Religion you thought true, hinder you in the middle of this enquiry, and that by a miſtaken humility, you dare not contradict your Miniſters, for your Fathers did not adhere to the new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, in forſaking the Church, but becauſe they had inſpired them with that criminal preſumption, that they ought not make account of the Fathers or Councils, but every one could, and ought to make himſelf Judge of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:137243:88"/>and Councils, by the light he ſhould imagine to have found in the Scripture, after having invocated the Holy Spirit: it is moſt juſt you make uſe of the ſame Priviledge, in reſpect of your new Maſters, ſeeing hitherto they have not taken the boldneſs to ſay they were the only men who might be followed with all ſecurity, and without any ground of fear of being miſled. This is all I ask of you, your Miniſters have ſo often told you, that you muſt not believe men in matter of Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all men are lyars. Begine at them with the Practiſe of this Rule, and with judging of the Rule it ſelf, for perhaps it's not ſo generally true as they pretend: but making it general they cannot ſay it's not true in reſpect of them.</p>
               <p>I doubt not but you will confeſs they have ſtill repreſented to you <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> which they call a Monſter, and <hi>the adoration of Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacrament,</hi> which they call Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
<pb n="461" facs="tcp:137243:88"/>
                  <hi>as two things unknown to the whole world, ſave only to the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, and that neither the</hi> Greeks, <hi>nor the</hi> Arminians, <hi>nor the</hi> Ruſſians, <hi>nor the</hi> Jacobits, <hi>nor the</hi> Ethiopians, <hi>nor generally, any Chriſtian beſide thoſe who ſubmit to the Pope, believes any thing of theſe two Articles.</hi> Theſe are Mr. <hi>Claud</hi>'s words, (<hi>Preface of his anſwer to Mr.</hi> Arnaud, <hi>pag.</hi> 759) and as they all look upon him, as the great Defender of the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, it's very like they all ſpeak the ſame Language, &amp; though they ſhould not ſo boldly maintain ſo great a falſhood, it's moſt certain they are very careful to conceal from you the general agreement of all theſe great Societies with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, not only in point of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> but likewiſe in many other points; as the Sacrifice of the Maſs, Prayer for the Dead, the Invocation of Saints, the Honour of their Images and Reliques, for which they have always induced
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:137243:89"/>you to condemn us as ſuperſtitious, and Idolaters. You cannot now doubt any more, that they have maliciouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed the Truth to you, concerning all this; what confidence then can you have in them, in beholding clearly that they cheat you in matters of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, where your Salvation is at the ſtake.</p>
               <p>Perhaps you will ſay, there is none but Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> who is guilty of this fault, and that it's true he is much to be blamed, for denying things ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, as is the great agreement of all thoſe Churches with the <hi>Roman,</hi> in all theſe Points. But as we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhown them, <hi>(Tom.</hi> 3 <hi>of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity, pag,</hi> 805.) that it was not,
<q>to take part in a procedure ſo unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming, and diſingenuous, as is that of Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> to have ſuffered in a common Cauſe, that he who had taken upon him their defence, ſhould eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it upon a notorious falſhood, and for four or five years debate, about a
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:137243:89"/>matter of fact, which ingenuity &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity ought to have made be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the firſt day, ought they not to have publickly diſaproved this proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and not have permitted, that in the enterpriſe of defending what they take for truth, the truth ſhould be wounded by impoſing upon the whole '<hi>East,</hi> to believe what it believes not.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Mean while, conſider if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miniſter who diſaproved Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> during ſo long a time as that Diſpute laſted, and very far from that, there is very lately one of the moſt Famous and Learned Profeſſours, (Mr. <hi>Spanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi>) of the united <hi>Provinces,</hi> who heaps up Praiſes on Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> for the advantages he pretends he has carried in this Diſpute, whereof the chief Point was to know, if the Oriental Churches, did really agree with the <hi>Roman,</hi> in point of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and who with a wonderful confidence, affirms that his Illuſtrious Brother has expoſed to open view, the <hi>vanity of the ſuppoſitions</hi> of
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:137243:90"/>his Adverſary, by which he can mean no other but the principal matter of fact, which the Author of the <hi>Perpetuity</hi> had taken for the ground of his whole Diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that all the Churches of the World were united in the Faith of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> in the time of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> as they are likewiſe at this preſent time. Lo here what Mr. <hi>Spanhemius</hi> dares call <hi>moſt falſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, vaniſſimas Hypotheſes,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' you ſee with your own eyes, that they are undenyable truths. But you ought to be much more aſtoniſhed to ſee that he is not aſhamed, to make the moſt authentick, and moſt ſolemn atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, that ever a Church did give of her Faith, paſs for precarious Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which ought not be noticed, as having been given by Mercenary Souls, who betrayed their Conſcience, in letting themſelves be corrupted for money, <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>of the Perpet.</hi> 806.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>For what can you conclude from that but that among thoſe of your Party, no
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:137243:90"/>reguard is had to the truth, and thoſe who reigns in it, by the confidence people has in them, and by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they attribute to themſelves, care not by what means they keep the People adhereing to them; that falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods are equally good to them as truths, when they produce this effect, and provyding an Author make noiſe, and be able to amuſe the World with the ſound of his words, the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent amongſt the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> are glad to let him be doing, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders always as an advantage, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion they make thereby upon the generality of their Party.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But you ought not ſtop here, it is yet more important for you to conſider that Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> did not engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the denyal of ſo certain matters of fact, and the other Miniſters to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud his Art, to colour theſe falſhoods, but becauſe they ſaw no other way to extricate themſelves from the difficulty they were in. To ſuppoſe, as they did,
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:137243:91"/>that all the Churches of the world had been for nine Ages, without believing the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> and to find them all united in this Belief at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the eleventh Age, without that any one perceived this change, or any mark or memory of it remaining, is a <hi>Chimere</hi> ſo abſurd to be maintained, that they themſelves were amazed at it. Therefore to give it a little more likly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, it was needful, to reſtrict this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation, within the limits of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, and to pretend that all the reſt had not changed, and were all <hi>Berengarians,</hi> and had always been ſuch, when <hi>Berengarius</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Weſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You cannot then be perſwaded of the contrary (as there is no man of good ſence, but ought to be, by only reading what I have ſaid in the 1 and 2 <hi>Sect.</hi> and yet more by reading the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I have marked of the 1 <hi>Tom</hi> of the <hi>Perpet.</hi>) you cannot, I ſay, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the agreement of the <hi>Greek</hi>
                  <pb n="297" facs="tcp:137243:91"/>Church of that time, but you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that, that pretended Innovation, without which, <hi>Calviniſm</hi> cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, is a work of the Father of Lyes, for it ought to have had place in all the Churches of the World, as well as in the <hi>Roman;</hi> which they well ſaw was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable, as Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> cryes out for fear, leſt he be neceſſitate to ſhew how its poſſible that inſenſible change was made at the ſame time, over all the World, <hi>The Queſtion is not of the whole World, The Queſtion is of the Occident, and of the Provinces ſubject to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the condition of the <hi>Greeks</hi> at preſent, and of all the other Oriental Communions threw back your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters into the ſame difficulty: for if they had granted, that they alſo held all at preſent the <hi>Real Preſence, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubstantiation,</hi> and the <hi>Adoration,</hi> and are perſwaded they never had another Faith, whom could they have made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that this had happened four or five hundred years ſince, by an inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:137243:92"/>change in all theſe Communions, of whom many have no connexion with one another, it being they mutually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe others of Hereſie, without ſo much as one perſon perceiving the Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore it was needful to ſay farther, that it was falſe the Oriental Churches were of this Faith, and that this could not be true, but only of ſome Latiniſed <hi>Greeks,</hi> and not at all of the true <hi>Greeks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they are of this Faith, whether Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> will or not, you are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perſwaded thereof. But beware, leſt for want of application, to the moſt important Affair you have in the world, which is that of your Salvation, you ſmother the natural conſequences you ought to draw from this conviction, for you ought to ſay,</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1. Our Miniſters have cheated us hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, in denying many years perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naciouſly, and as far as can be judged againſt their own Conſciences, in a diſpute of Religion, a thing which is
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:137243:92"/>more clear than the light of the day, we have then no reaſon to truſt our ſelves to ſo blind guids, and ſo void of ſincerity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They deny or diſſemble matters of fact, ſo certain and important to be known, for no other Reaſon, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being acknowledged to be true, the pretended Innovation in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> in all the Churches of the World cannot ſubſiſt; I cannot then be convinced, as I am of the truth of theſe matters of fact, but I muſt alſo be convinced that that Innovation is a dream invented by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertin</hi> and other Miniſters, becauſe they ſaw well without that they could not hinder themſelves from being looked upon as Innovators and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Its not only in the belief of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that theſe great Oriental Societies agree with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; it is alſo in the Sacrifice of the Maſs, in Prayer for the Dead, in
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:137243:93"/>the Invocation of Saints, in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour given to their Reliques and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which our Miniſters inceſſantly repreſent to us, as Doctrins of <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> for which we ought to have made ſeparation from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and which are the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſubject of their invectives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now I ſee clearly all that is ill grounded, ſince all other Chriſtian Communions, who are not ſubject to that pretended <hi>Antechrist,</hi> have on all that, the ſame Faith which the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks have: I have therefore great reaſon to fear, that I cannot in conſcience continue to ſtay with Calumniators and Schiſmaticks, and conſequently, I cannot do better than to return back whence our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ought not to have come forth:</p>
               </q>
               <p>I think there is no intelligent Perſon will deny theſe conſequences to be juſt; yet it is ſo great a matter to change Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that the conviction of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is not ſufficient for that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:137243:93"/>God muſt beſides, touch the Heart with his Grace, Prayer muſt beg this Favour from him, and Hope muſt expect it from his Mercy.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:94"/>
            <head>Approbation of the <hi>Doctors,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>WE underwritten</hi> Doctors <hi>in Theologie, of the faculty of</hi> Paris, <hi>do certify we have read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Book, Entituled,</hi> The Faith of the Catholick Church concerning the Euchariſt, <hi>invincibly proved,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>with a Preface in form of a Letter to the Gentlemen of the pretended Reformed Religion, by M— We have found them conform to the Rules of Faith, and moſt profitable for the converſion of Heriticks: The Author ſets down therein, in Abridgement, what is contained in ſeveral Volumns, to the end he might facilitate the means of being inſtructed of the Truth of this great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, to thoſe who might not have the leaſure to read theſe Volumns entirely. This is the judgement we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke of this little, but excellent Work, at</hi> Paris, <hi>the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of</hi> November, 1683.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>AUGET of the Houſe of <hi>Sorbon,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>RICHER of the Houſe of <hi>Navarr.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:137243:94"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
